<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!-- vim: set filetype=docbkxml encoding=utf8: -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//JediRy//DTD DocBook XML-MathML-SVG V4.3//EN"
  "http://jediry.com/xml/docbook/docbook4.3-mathml-svg.dtd">


<chapter id="Conclusion">
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <para>
    Terrain generation is a topic of interest to practitioners in a number of 
    fields, some of which are entertainment- and art-related, with others being 
    more utilitarian in nature. This topic has received significantly less 
    treatment in the literature than has the related topic of real-time terrain 
    visualization. Terrain generation methods currently in practice are usually  
    fractal in nature, and are often difficult to control.
  </para>
  <para>
    <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> is a new, user-friendly method of 
    generating an effectively unlimited diversity of 3D terrain models. It 
    differs from current state-of-the-art methods for terrain generation in a 
    number of ways, in particular:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        it uses user-provided, real-world elevation data as raw material.  
        Because of this, a user can extend the capabilities of the system 
        without changing the fundamental algorithm, simply by adding examples of 
        new types of terrain.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        it follows a user-centric design paradigm, where types of terrain are 
        described by example, and the desired arrangement of these terrain types 
        is specified in an intuitive manner (i.e., by drawing a map). In this 
        paradigm, the user is freed from nearly all of the manual labor that 
        characterizes manual "sculpting" methods for height field creation, and 
        is not required to learn esoteric skills in order to get a desired 
        result, as in many procedural methods.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        it uses artificial intelligence techniques, specifically genetic 
        algorithms, to generate a height field approximating the user's design 
        and manifesting the appropriate terrain characteristics in each distinct 
        region. To my knowledge, this is the first significant attempt to apply 
        artificial intelligence techniques to the problem of terrain 
        generation.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    The second contribution of <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> is a 
    paradigm for terrain generation in which the user is freed from almost all 
    of the burden of constructing the terrain, while at the same time still 
    retaining some control over the shape of the terrain. All of the inputs 
    expected of the user are intuitive to grasp. Furthermore, it is not 
    necessary for the user to understand how 
    <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> works in order to use it effectively.  
    These characteristics will become increasingly important in the future as 
    the scale of virtual worlds continues to increase&em;development teams 
    simply will not have the time to design the terrain manually.
  </para>
  <para>
    The third contribution of <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> is a new 
    method of performing approximate comparisons of terrain height fields using 
    a variation on statistical distribution matching. This comparison method is 
    adaptive, is not highly sensitive to differences in the size or shape of 
    the terrains being compared, and has a built-in measure of how well it is 
    performing in any given case.
  </para>
  <para>
    <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>, while not as trivial to implement as 
    more simplistic algorithms, could be of enormous use in a studio authoring 
    environment, especially when integrated with 3D modeling tools for manual 
    fine-tuning. Towards this end, it would be useful to implement this 
    algorithm as a plugin for one or more currently popular 3D modeling 
    packages.
  </para>
  <para>
    Obviously, terrain generation is not yet a solved problem. The positive 
    results produced by <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> suggest that even 
    more promising results will emerge with additional research. It is my 
    belief that future research in this field ought to pursue a course similar 
    to <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>'s&em;the use of artificial 
    intelligence techniques seems a promising road (and perhaps the 
    <emphasis>most</emphasis> promising) for doing terrain generation in a way 
    that is both realistic and user-friendly.
  </para>
</chapter>
