<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!-- vim: set filetype=docbkxml encoding=utf8: -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//JediRy//DTD DocBook XML-MathML-SVG V4.3//EN"
  "http://jediry.com/xml/docbook/docbook4.3-mathml-svg.dtd">

<chapter id="Background">
  <title>Background</title>
  <para>
    In this chapter, I cover a number of topics that serve as necessary 
    background material for understanding the 
    <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> algorithm. First, I survey the history 
    and state-of-the-art in virtual terrain, and then highlight several previous 
    works that are especially similar to <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>.  
    Finally, I touch upon several auxiliary topics that are directly relevant to 
    <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>.
  </para>

  <section id="Previous Work">
    <title>Previous Work in Virtual Terrain</title>
    <para>
      In order to understand the relationship of 
      <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> to the field of terrain generation, 
      it is helpful to have a grasp of the scope of current terrain generation 
      literature and praxis. To this end, in this section, I review the 
      following topics:
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          a brief discussion of the issues involved in mapping ellipsoid 
          objects (e.g., the Earth)
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          a survey of different structures for representing terrain, with their 
          benefits and drawbacks
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          a taxonomy of existing methods of generating terrain
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          a discussion of level of detail issues in terrain generation
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          a survey of existing terrain generation software
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          pointers to terrain-related sites on the Internet
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <section id="Geodetic Mapping">
      <title>Geodetic Mapping</title>
      <para>
        The Earth (and the other planets) are (roughly) ellipsoidal objects of 
        enormous size. In most aspects of our everyday life, it suffices to 
        think of the Earth simply as an infinite plane, completely flat. Only 
        when we deal with a planet at larger scales (e.g., for global 
        positioning and navigation) does it become necessary to account for the 
        effects of planetary curvature.
      </para>
      <para>
        Researchers in the cartographic and astronomic sciences have been 
        devising schemes for dealing with these effects for a long time. With 
        the rise of computing technology, the field of <firstterm>Geographic 
          Information Systems (GIS)</firstterm>, the application of computers 
        to mapping and understanding the Earth, has made great use of these 
        schemes to produce digital maps of most of the Earth's surface. Still, 
        GIS mapping is not without its difficulties, many of them due to 
        attempting to "unwrap" the ellipsoidal planet surface to produce a 
        planar representation of the geography; there appears to be no natural 
        way of doing this. A full discussion of the difficulties of planetary 
        mapping, and their work-arounds, is outside of the scope of this 
        thesis, but to name a few:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          One way of producing a planar surface from an ellipsoidal surface is 
          to map the ellipsoid using a spherical coordinate system, and then to 
          create a rectangular map with the latitude and longitude as the two 
          axes. The major problem with this approach is that distances become 
          more and more distorted towards the poles. For a digital terrain 
          model, this means that if the surface is sampled uniformly in the 
          latitude/longitude coordinate system, the sample points will not be 
          uniformly distributed across the surface of the sphere, but will be 
          denser around the poles.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Another way of producing a planar surface is to "slice" the ellipsoid 
          like an orange and to flatten each slice of the map with a local 
          planar projection. This results in less distortion, but causes 
          discontinuities in the planar map and creates large areas in the map 
          that do not correspond to any point on the ellipsoid.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      For more information on geodetic mapping, projection &amp; coordinate 
      systems, and GIS in general, the USGS's website is a good place to start 
      <biblioref linkend="USGS"/>.
    </section>

    <section id="Terrain Representations">
      <title>Methods of Representing Terrain</title>
      <para>
        One of the most fundamental decisions to be made when working with 
        virtual terrain is that of how to <emphasis>represent</emphasis> the 
        terrain. The choice of data structure will affect the set of available 
        tools in our terrain generation "toolbox", and may also limit the kinds 
        of terrain features that can be represented or the ways in which the 
        terrain can be edited and used. Some questions that must be answered 
        based on the needs of the application include:
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            Does the terrain need to have infinite precision, such that it can 
            be viewed at any arbitrary scale, or is it acceptable to have a 
            finite, maximal resolution?
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Is it important to be able to represent terrain structures like 
            caves and overhangs, in which multiple surfaces have the same 
            horizontal coordinates, or will the terrain surface obey the 
            vertical line test at every point?
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Are the effects of planetary curvature important, or is a "flat 
            Earth" approximation good enough?
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Will the terrain surface need to be rendered and/or tested for 
            object collisions in an efficient manner?
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        In light of these considerations, we can compare the merits and 
        limitations of several alternative representations for terrain:
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            height fields
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            voxel grids
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            non-uniform meshes
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            analytic and fractal functions
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <section id="Height Fields">
        <title>Height Fields</title>
        <para>
          The terrain representation most widely used at the present time is 
          probably the <firstterm>height field</firstterm>. A height field 
          represents a surface as a scalar function of two discrete variables, 
          such that the horizontal coordinate pair
          <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/(x,y).mml"/></inlineequation> 
          determines the elevation at that point. While there is nothing 
          precluding the use of an infinite, continuous function or a 
          non-rectangular domain, in usual practice, this function is 
          discretized at regular intervals in <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/x.mml"/></inlineequation> and 
          <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/y.mml"/></inlineequation>, 
          with <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/x.mml"/></inlineequation> and 
          <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/y.mml"/></inlineequation> 
          valid over a finite, rectangular domain, the width and height of the 
          height field (<xref linkend="Height Field Equation"/>).
        </para>
        <equation id="Height Field Equation">
          <title>Height Field Equation</title>
          <xi:include href="resources/Height Field Equation.mml"/>
        </equation>
        <para>
          This formulation leads to the familiar implementation of the height 
          field as a 2D array of scalar elevation values (<xref linkend="Height 
            Field Image"/>).
        </para>
        <figure id="Height Field Image">
          <title>A Discrete Height Field</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata scalefit="1" width="5in"
                         fileref="Height Field Wireframe.jpeg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <section>
          <title>Advantages of Height Fields</title>
          <para>
            Once we observe that the discrete form of the height field is 
            essentially the same thing as a greyscale image, this quickly leads 
            us to the insight that computer vision and image processing 
            techniques may be used to construct, modify, analyze, and compress 
            terrain models represented as height fields (for example, a rough 
            terrain could be made smoother by applying a standard Gaussian blur 
            filter to it, and a height field can be stored using an image file 
            format).
          </para>
          <para>
            A second advantage of the height field is that its regular 
            structure makes it possible to optimize operations like rendering, 
            collision-detection and path-finding. The rendering of even very 
            large height fields in real-time has been made feasible by the 
            invention of a number of <firstterm>continuous level of detail 
              (CLOD) algorithms</firstterm>, which render highly visible areas 
            of the terrain with detailed geometry, using progressively simpler 
            geometry for obscured or more distant parts of the terrain 
            <biblioref linkend="ROAM"/> <biblioref linkend="Chunked LOD"/> 
            <biblioref linkend="Feature-based CLOD"/> <biblioref 
              linkend="Geometry Clipmaps"/>. Collision detection, an expensive 
            operation in the general case, can be done cheaply when one of the 
            objects is a height field since, given an
            <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/(x,y).mml"/></inlineequation>
            location in the height field, only a few surrounding triangles need 
            to be checked for collision.
          </para>
          <para>
            A third advantage is that significant quantities of real-world 
            terrain data are available in height field form, making it the 
            representation of choice for working with GIS data.
          </para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Disadvantages of Height Fields</title>
          <para>
            The most fundamental disadvantage of the height field is that, 
            since surface elevation is a function of an
            <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/(x,y).mml"/></inlineequation>
            coordinate pair, there must be exactly one elevation for every pair 
            of coordinates. Because of this, a height field is inherently unable 
            to represent caves, overhangs, vertical surfaces, and other terrain 
            structures in which multiple surfaces have the same horizontal 
            coordinates (<xref linkend="Height Field Cartoon"/>). In practice, 
            this limitation is often inconsequential, since most natural terrain 
            is fairly "well behaved" in this respect, and the exceptional cases 
            can be handled by modeling overlapping structures as separate 
            objects placed atop the terrain (though this solution does have an 
            undesirable <foreignphrase>ad hoc</foreignphrase> quality to it).
          </para>
          <figure id="Height Field Cartoon">
            <title>The Problem With Height Fields</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <caption>
                One of the main disadvantages of height fields is that they are 
                inherently limited in the kinds of features that they can 
                capture; features such as overhangs and caves cannot be 
                represented in a standard height field.
              </caption>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata scalefit="1" width="80%"
                           fileref="Height Field Cartoon.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            A second disadvantage of the height field, when used in its usual, 
            discrete form, is that it has a finite, uniform resolution.  This 
            has two negative implications. First, because the resolution is 
            <emphasis>finite</emphasis>, this places a firm upper bound on the 
            degree of fine-scale detail that the height field can represent.  As 
            a result, when viewed from a too-close viewpoint, the terrain may 
            appear blocky, featureless and unnatural. Second, because the 
            resolution is <emphasis>uniform</emphasis> throughout the domain, a 
            a height field cannot gracefully handle terrains having a highly 
            variable local level of detail. If the resolution is chosen to match 
            the average scale of the features in the terrain, then any 
            finer-scale features will be simplified or eliminated; conversely, 
            if the resolution is chosen to be high enough to capture the 
            fine-scale features, areas containing only coarse features will also 
            be captured at this same high resolution, an undesirable waste of 
            space and processing time. Ideally, a terrain representation for 
            terrain generation would either be infinite in resolution, or else 
            would adaptively increase its resolution to accommodate the addition 
            of fine scale details, rather than requiring an <foreignphrase>a 
              priori</foreignphrase> decision about resolution.
          </para>
          <para>
            A third disadvantage of the height field, if used to represent 
            terrain on a planetary scale, is that rectangular height field 
            patches do not map onto spheroid objects any better than rectangular 
            image textures do.  If the standard, two-pole spherical projection 
            is used to map a height field onto a spherical planet, the density 
            of height field points will be substantially greater in areas near 
            the poles than at those near the equator.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Voxel Grids</title>
        <para>
          Another possibility for representing terrain is the height field's 3D 
          cousin, the <firstterm>voxel grid</firstterm>. A voxel grid is a 
          discrete, three-dimensional grid of <firstterm>voxels</firstterm> 
          (the volumetric equivalent of pixels), in which (in the simplest 
          case) each voxel is either filled or not. By selectively filling 
          voxels, one can create arbitrary 3D shapes.
        </para>

        <section>
          <title>Advantages of Voxel Grids</title>
          <para>
            The main advantage that voxel grids have over height fields is that 
            they are not constrained by the vertical line test, and can 
            represent vertical surfaces, overhangs, etc.
          </para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Disadvantages of Voxel Grids</title>
          <para>
            Voxel grids inherit most of the problems of height fields, and add 
            several of their own. They share the height field's disadvantages 
            of having a finite resolution, and of not handling planetary 
            curvature gracefully. Rendering and collision detection are more 
            expensive than with height fields, and more data must be pushed to 
            the graphics card for the same amount of rendered horizontal area.  
            Additionally, without the use of spatial subdivision techniques 
            (such as octrees), voxel grids are typically very wasteful of 
            memory (as large chunks of the grid are either completely empty or 
            are buried deep underground).
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Non-uniform Meshes</title>
        <para>
          A more general way of handling terrain is to represent the surface of  
          the terrain as an arbitrary mesh of 2D primitives (usually polygons, 
          but sometimes quadric or cubic Bezier or NURBS patches) embedded in 
          the 3D space. Such mesh surfaces are popular ways of modeling and 
          animating characters and other objects, and there are numerous tools 
          available for working with objects in this form.
        </para>
        <para>
          A <firstterm>triangular irregular network (TIN)</firstterm> 
          <biblioref linkend="TIN"/> is a special case of a non-uniform mesh.  
          In a TIN, the surface is represented as a mesh of triangles derived 
          from a set of 3D points (using, for example, the Delunay 
          triangulation). TINs are useful ways of creating a mesh 
          representation from real-world data&em;the points, called 
          <firstterm>mass points</firstterm>, could be sampled directly from 
          the terrain surface, or could be derived from the contours of a 
          topographic map.
        </para>

        <section>
          <title>Advantages of Meshes</title>
          <para>
            The main benefit of using meshes to model the terrain surface is 
            that they are extremely general. The surface may have arbitrary 
            geometry and topology (overhangs, caves, rock arches, etc.), and an 
            artist working with meshes is free to model even the most bizarre 
            and heterogeneous terrain structures using a single modeling 
            paradigm.
          </para>
          <para>
            A second advantage of meshes is that they naturally support variable 
            level of detail, allowing more vertices in areas of sharp change and 
            relatively few vertices in flat areas. As a result, a mesh structure 
            can store some terrain models much more efficiently than regular 
            grid methods, since it does not require a globally high resolution 
            in order to achieve fine-scale features in a few places.
          </para>
          <para>
            Furthermore, as most of the tools for computer modeling and 
            animation support this paradigm, there is a significant user base 
            that is already comfortable with manipulating objects represented 
            in this way.
          </para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Disadvantages of Meshes</title>
          <para>
            The main difficulty with using meshes for terrain generation is that 
            it is not clear how to generate them automatically; even though 
            terrain is almost always tessellated into some sort of polygonal 
            representation before rendering, I am unaware of any terrain 
            generation methods (other than manual sculpting) that work directly 
            on a mesh representation (i.e., without the use of a more 
            constrained, terrain-specific data structure).
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Continuous Functions</title>
        <para>
          A final possibility is to represent the terrain with some sort of 
          analytic or fractal function. This approach is seldom used in 
          practice, with the <citetitle>MojoWorld</citetitle> world generator 
          being a rare, but impressive example <biblioref linkend="MojoWorld"/>.
        </para>

        <section>
          <title>Advantages of Continuous Functions</title>
          <para>
            Continuous functions (both analytic and fractal) have the advantage 
            of being viewable at any scale without losing resolution; viewed 
            close-up, they do not look "faceted" as height fields tend to do.  
            Beyond this, both analytic and fractal functions have their own 
            advantages.
          </para>
          <para>
            Certain classes of analytic functions offer mathematical advantages 
            that make them friendly for rendering and/or collision 
            detection/response. Many types of analytic functions are 
            differentiable at most or all points, allowing precise derivatives 
            to be calculated. Polynomial surfaces of low degree (quartic and 
            below) have closed-form solutions, allowing ray/surface 
            intersections to be calculated in a straightforward way.
          </para>
          <para>
            Fractals offer a different advantage: unlike analytic functions, 
            which typically become more and more linear when viewed at finer and  
            finer scales, fractal functions continue to produce new details as 
            they are evaluated at progressively finer scales, meaning that a 
            fractal terrain can have as much fine-scale detail as the display 
            system can render.
          </para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Disadvantages of Continuous Functions</title>
          <para>
            The main problem of using continuous functions is the difficulty of 
            modeling with them. If a single, global function is used, it is 
            difficult to know how to modify the function to achieve a certain 
            local effect. A more usable approach is to compose a number of 
            functions, each having a local area of effect (B-spline patches are 
            example of this), though this has yet to replace polygon-based 
            techniques as the dominant modeling paradigm.
          </para>
          <para>
            The other drawback of continuous functions is the difficulty of 
            rendering them. For a polygon-based rendering system, the function 
            must be transformed into a form that the graphics hardware can 
            process (e.g., triangles). For a ray tracing system, the first 
            intersection of a ray with the surface must be evaluated.  In 
            either case, depending on the complexity and topology of the 
            function, this process may be quite expensive.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="Taxonomy of Methods">
      <title>A Taxonomy of Terrain Generation Methods</title>
      <para>
        Terrain generation has not received nearly as much attention in the 
        literature as terrain LOD rendering has, with relatively few 
        innovations to date. The discussion of terrain generation in the 
        computer science literature dates back at least as far as 1977, to a 
        paper in which terrain created from simple mathematical functions is 
        used to stage simulated military combat scenarios <biblioref 
          linkend="Combat Simulation"/>. Since that time, a variety of methods  
        for producing terrain have been proposed, generally falling into four 
        broad categories:
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            GIS-based methods
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Sculpting methods
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Simulation methods
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Procedural methods
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <section id="GIS-based Methods">
        <title>GIS-based Methods</title>
        <figure id="GIS-based Methods Skill Chart">
          <title>Typical Characteristics of GIS-based Methods</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              GIS-based methods are simple to implement, and borrow their 
              realism directly from the real world, but are limited to the 
              locations and resolutions for which real-world data is available.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Skill Chart - GIS.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          The most obvious place to find natural-looking terrain is in nature 
          itself. While not strictly a method of 
          <emphasis>generating</emphasis> terrain, the use of GIS data is a 
          simple and effective way of getting very realistic terrain models 
          (<xref linkend="GIS-based Methods Skill Chart"/>).  High-quality 
          elevation maps (height fields) of the entire United States (and some 
          other parts of the world) can be downloaded or ordered from a variety 
          of GIS data providers (such as <citetitle>Geo Community</citetitle> 
          <biblioref linkend="GeoCommunity"/> and the <citetitle>U.S.  
            Geological Survey (USGS)</citetitle> <biblioref linkend="USGS 
            Maps"/>).  These data are available in several formats (with older 
          elevation maps available in the DEM format <biblioref linkend="DEM 
            Specification"/> and more recent data available only in the more 
          complex SDTS format <biblioref linkend="SDTS Specification"/>) and at 
          resolutions as high as 3 meters per sample in some cases (though 
          resolutions of 10 and 30 meters per sample are much more 
          commonplace).
        </para>
        <para>
          GIS data is ideal when the overriding concern is realism, and is 
          often the best or only option when an application needs to represent 
          actual, real-world locations faithfully. Applications of this sort 
          include mapping software <biblioref linkend="ArcGIS"/> and 
          simulations set in real-world locations <biblioref linkend="SimCity 
            4"/> <biblioref linkend="FS 2004"/>. Using GIS data, a high degree 
          of realism can be achieved for relatively little human effort.
        </para>
        <para>
          The major drawback to the use of GIS data is the constraint that it 
          imposes: only real-world locations that are present in a mapping 
          agency's database can be used. Thus, while little or no effort is 
          required to <emphasis>use</emphasis> GIS data in an application, 
          <emphasis>finding</emphasis> suitable data may be time-consuming or 
          simply impossible. For many applications, this may unacceptably 
          compromise artistic objectives (e.g., a movie director may want a 
          particular arrangement of mountains and rivers) or other, more 
          utilitarian goals (e.g., a particular military combat scenario might 
          require a particular set of terrain features). A secondary 
          disadvantage of GIS-based methods is the significant amount of space 
          required to store large datasets.  Finally, the level of detail 
          available through GIS sources is limited&em;if a particular 
          application requires finer-scale detail than that offered by the 
          mapping agency, one will have to resort to other means for achieving 
          it.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="Sculpting Methods">
        <title>Sculpting Methods</title>
        <figure id="Sculpting Methods Skill Chart">
          <title>Typical Characteristics of Sculpting Methods</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              Sculpting methods allow the terrain author to construct virtually 
              anything imaginable, but require significant effort and skill.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Skill Chart - Sculpting.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          At the opposite end of the spectrum, in terms of human effort, is the 
          use of artistic tools to "paint" or "sculpt" the features of the 
          terrain (<xref linkend="Sculpting Methods Skill Chart"/>).  In most 
          cases, this means using computer-based modeling and painting tools 
          (such as <citetitle>Adobe Photoshop</citetitle>, <citetitle>Bryce 
            3D</citetitle>, or <citetitle>Maya</citetitle>) or specialized 
          "level editors" (such as those shipped with the recent game titles 
          <citetitle>SimCity 4</citetitle> <biblioref linkend="SimCity 4"/> and 
          <citetitle>Unreal Tournament 2004</citetitle> <biblioref linkend="UT 
            2004"/>). Less commonly, an artist might create a model using 
          traditional, physical media and then digitize it using laser scanning 
          techniques, as was done to create the terrain for the video game 
          title <citetitle>Trespasser</citetitle> <biblioref 
            linkend="Trespasser Postmortem"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
          The primary advantage of sculpting methods is the enormous freedom 
          given to the artist. Anything the artist can conceive, he can 
          achieve, given sufficient skill and effort.
        </para>
        <para>
          This strength is also its main drawback&em;achieving a desired result 
          with this method typically requires a large investment of human time 
          and effort, and the quality of the results is heavily dependent on 
          the skill of the artist. As the size of the virtual environment 
          increases, so does the cost of sculpting it, making this method of 
          terrain generation less and less feasible as projects increase in 
          scope.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="Simulation Methods">
        <title>Simulation Methods</title>
        <figure id="Simulation Methods Skill Chart">
          <title>Typical Characteristics of Simulation Methods</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              Simulation methods have high potential for realism, but are 
              computationally expensive and difficult to control.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Skill Chart - Simulation.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Another family of terrain generation methods involves the evolution 
          of terrain by simulating the effects of physical processes such as 
          plate tectonics or erosion by wind or water <biblioref 
            linkend="Stream Erosion"/> <biblioref linkend="Eroded Fractal 
            Terrains"/> <biblioref linkend="Area51"/> <biblioref 
            linkend="Erosion 3D"/> (<xref linkend="Simulation Methods Skill 
            Chart"/>).  Simulation techniques for terrain generation have been 
          explored to a much smaller extent than other methods.
        </para>
        <para>
          These methods have the potential to produce highly realistic results,  
          to the extent that they accurately model the physical processes they 
          are intended to simulate. They can also be very hands-off, requiring 
          little input from the user.
        </para>
        <para>
          One drawback of simulation methods is the amount of processing time 
          required. In order for the simulation to produce realistic results, it 
          must run at sufficiently fine resolutions in both space and time to 
          adequately capture the effects of these processes; as the resolution 
          of the simulation increases, so does the time required to run it. A 
          second drawback of such methods is the relative lack of user control: 
          since a simulation is intended to capture the effects of natural 
          processes, the role of the human user is limited to setting up the 
          initial conditions for the simulation and kicking it off&em;achieving 
          specific, user-specified effects may be difficult.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="Procedural Methods">
        <title>Procedural Methods</title>
        <figure id="Procedural Methods Skill Chart">
          <title>Typical Characteristics of Procedural Methods</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              Procedural methods are often simple to implement, relatively fast 
              to run, somewhat difficult to control, and limited in realism.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Skill Chart - Procedural.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          The term "procedural methods" describes a broad family of terrain 
          generation techniques whose unifying factor is that they produce a 
          terrain model through the application of some sort of automatic 
          "procedure" (<xref linkend="Procedural Methods Skill Chart"/>). While 
          the aforementioned simulation methods (<xref linkend="Simulation 
            Methods"/>) fit this description, I consider them separately 
          because, unlike true simulation methods, most procedural generation 
          methods do not attempt to simulate any physical processes, and use 
          techniques that are quite different from the numeric integration that 
          is typical of simulations.  In most cases, procedural generation 
          methods are simply "hacks" that have been found to work acceptably for 
          generating certain types of terrain and rely heavily on random number 
          generation to produce irregular variations in the terrain surface.  
          Some of the earliest discussions in the literature focus on procedural 
          methods for approximating terrain <biblioref linkend="Combat 
            Simulation"/> <biblioref linkend="Procedure Models"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Some of the most popular procedural techniques are fractal in nature, 
          such as the midpoint displacement method (MPD) <biblioref 
            linkend="MPD Method"/> and Perlin Noise <biblioref linkend="Perlin 
            Noise"/>.  These techniques exhibit the fractal property of 
          self-similarity at different scales, and generally involve randomly 
          perturbing the height values of the terrain by increasingly smaller 
          amounts at increasingly finer scales.  Prusinkiewicz &amp; Hammel 
          describe a method for generating mountains with an integrated river 
          network that is entirely fractal in nature <biblioref 
            linkend="Mountains and Rivers"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
          A similar class of procedural techniques in current practice is known 
          as <firstterm>collaging</firstterm> or <firstterm>faulting</firstterm> 
          methods <biblioref linkend="Area51"/>.  In these techniques, an 
          irregular height field is created through the random superposition of 
          simple shapes, such as spheres, cones, half-planes, or 2D 
          trigonometric functions.  After several hundred to several thousand 
          iterations, the result is a random height field possessing similar 
          curvature and smoothness characteristics to the primitive shape, but 
          without any of the primitive shapes directly apparent in the terrain.
        </para>
        <para>
          Less frequently used are a family of <firstterm>spectral 
            synthesis</firstterm> techniques, which involve randomly or 
          semi-randomly constructing a frequency-spectrum (Fourier- or 
          wavelet-space) representation of a terrain and then performing the 
          inverse transform to produce the spatial representation of the 
          terrain <biblioref linkend="Wavelet Synthesis"/> <biblioref 
            linkend="Spectral Synthesis"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Procedural methods for terrain generation are popular among artists 
          and game designers <biblioref linkend="Lighthouse 3D"/> <biblioref 
            linkend="Fluid Simulation"/>, largely because they are easy to 
          understand and implement. They also generate unique and (ideally) 
          interesting results each time, and can run with little or no human 
          input in many cases, making them useful for generating random game 
          worlds. If used in this way, the application need not store any 
          height field data on disk, since a new, unique terrain environment 
          can be constructed each time the application runs.
        </para>
        <para>
          The principal drawback of these methods is that they generally have 
          no causal connection to the real-world terrain they try to emulate, 
          instead bearing only an incidental resemblance (in other words, they 
          only happen to <emphasis>look</emphasis> terrain-like rather than 
          being somehow <emphasis>derived from</emphasis> the same principles 
          and processes that cause the formation of real terrain).  Because of 
          this, most procedural methods are only useful for simulating a limited 
          range of terrain types. In addition, since the procedural parameters 
          do not typically correspond to real-world terrain characteristics (and 
          are often rather unintuitive), achieving a desired effect is likely to 
          be an exercise in trial and error.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="Level of Detail Considerations">
      <title>Level of Detail Considerations</title>
      <para>
        Another way of classifying terrain generation methods, essentially 
        orthogonal to the taxonomy of the previous section (<xref 
          linkend="Taxonomy of Methods"/>), is with respect to how they handle 
        level of detail.  In terrain rendering, LOD considerations are 
        important for handling large terrain models efficiently. In terrain 
        <emphasis>generation</emphasis>, however, LOD acquires a whole new 
        level of importance. In rendering, LOD may be thought of simply as an 
        upper limit on the amount of detail to be shown; in generation, LOD has 
        (or <emphasis>should</emphasis> have) an enormous impact on the shape 
        and features of the generated terrain. Terrain features occur across a 
        variety of scales, ranging from entire mountain ranges down to small 
        cracks in the ground. As the LOD of a terrain is reduced, the finer 
        details are lost, leaving only the larger features; because of this, we 
        may consider those details that disappeared as <emphasis>belonging 
          to</emphasis> the finer LOD, and we may design our algorithms to 
        exploit this. At least three classes of generation methods can be 
        distinguished with respect to LOD:
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            methods that are LOD-agnostic, and generate the full spectrum of 
            detail in one shot
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            methods that generate detail at different scales, and combine 
            them via superposition
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            methods that work from coarse to fine, progressively introducing 
            finer and finer modifications to the terrain
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        In the following sections, I describe these three classes of methods, 
        concluding with a discussion of the applicability of fractals to terrain 
        generation.
      </para>

      <section id="LOD-agnostic Methods">
        <title>LOD-agnostic Methods</title>
        <para>
          The most simplistic approach to LOD is, of course, to ignore it as 
          much as possible. A number of generation methods follow this course, 
          considering LOD only when initially selecting the resolution of the 
          height field (or other structure).
        </para>
        <para>
          Many of the procedural methods discussed in <xref linkend="Procedural 
          Methods"/> fit this description.  Collaging/faulting methods 
          <biblioref linkend="Area51"/> are a good example: the resolution of 
          the height field is fixed at the start of the algorithm, and the 
          collaging process runs to completion without explicit consideration 
          for the LOD of generated features.  The features produced, whether 
          large or small, are simply the consequence of the random overlapping 
          of hundreds or thousands of simple shapes.
        </para>
        <para>
          Another class of methods that is typically LOD-agnostic is the class  
          of simulation methods discussed in <xref linkend="Simulation 
            Methods"/>.  Since simulation is usually done using numerical 
          integration techniques on a regular grid structure, the initial 
          choices of grid resolution and simulation time-step are normally the 
          only points at which LOD considerations are consciously applied.  
          Thereafter, the physical features of the terrain emerge through the 
          approximation of physical processes, without further reference to LOD 
          (though the initial choice of LOD will certainly affect the accuracy 
          of the simulation).
        </para>
        <para>
          These examples are sufficient to illustrate the principal weakness of 
          most LOD-agnostic algorithms: because they do "everything at once", 
          with many overlapping effects, the effects of any individual step in 
          the generation process are difficult or impossible for the human user 
          to distinguish, making the generation process inscrutable, 
          unpredictable&hellip;and uncontrollable. As was mentioned in <xref 
          linkend="Simulation Methods"/>, physically-based simulations have the 
          drawback of being difficult for a user to guide towards a desired 
          result. This is partially attributable to the LOD-agnostic nature of 
          the simulation: a tweak to the initial conditions of the simulation 
          may (or may not) produce the desired effect at a certain scale, but 
          may also have undesired side-effects at larger or smaller scales.  
          Non-physically-based methods of the LOD-agnostic sort share this 
          characteristic of being opaque to the human user, and carry the 
          additional liability of tending to generate physically incorrect 
          shapes. It is difficult to see how such methods could ever rise above 
          the level of simple "hacks" to become controllable, realistic terrain 
          generators.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="Superposition Methods">
        <title>Superposition Methods</title>
        <para>
          A second approach to LOD is to construct detail in separate "layers" 
          of different scales, and then to combine these layers by adding them 
          together (employing <firstterm>superposition</firstterm>, to borrow 
          signal theory terminology). To understand the distinction between 
          these methods and the following class (<xref linkend="Progressive 
            Refinement Methods"/>), it is important to grasp that these 
          different layers are not <emphasis>themselves</emphasis> the LODs of 
          the terrain, but only the details belonging to a finite "slice" of the 
          frequency spectrum. The actual LODs can be reconstituted by summing 
          together all of the layers up to the requisite degree of fineness.
        </para>
        <para>
          Spectral synthesis methods <biblioref linkend="Wavelet Synthesis"/> 
          <biblioref linkend="Spectral Synthesis"/> take precisely this 
          approach: by setting the values of the various frequency-domain 
          coefficients, one can control the presence and importance of details 
          at different scales. The recombination of these different scales into 
          a spatial-domain height field is done by applying the appropriate 
          inverse transform (Fourier or wavelet) to the frequency-domain 
          representation.
        </para>
        <para>
          Another example of a superposition method is Perlin Noise <biblioref 
            linkend="Perlin Noise"/>, in which random noise layers of different 
          frequencies and amplitudes are added together; the choice of 
          frequency and amplitude for each of the layers gives some measure of 
          control over the overall characteristics of the resulting height 
          field.
        </para>
        <para>
          The practical success of Perlin Noise in computer graphics can be 
          largely attributed to its versatility. Compared to the LOD-agnostic 
          methods previously discussed (<xref linkend="LOD-agnostic 
            Methods"/>), Perlin Noise (and similar superposition methods) allow 
          a user to achieve a greater variety of effects, by allowing him to 
          exert some degree of predictable control over the behavior of the 
          surface at different scales.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="Progressive Refinement Methods">
        <title>Progressive Refinement Methods</title>
        <para>
          A third approach to LOD in terrain generation is to refine the terrain 
          surface progressively, starting from a coarse LOD and adding finer and 
          finer details until the desired LOD is reached.  These methods differ 
          from those in the previous section (<xref linkend="Superposition 
            Methods"/>) in that they construct new, fine-scale details as 
          modifications to the coarser LODs.
        </para>
        <para>
          These methods often work by recursive subdivision: given a complete,  
          coarse LOD of the terrain, the next-finer LOD is constructed by 
          subdividing the coarse LOD and, at the same time, introducing new, 
          small-scale modifications to the terrain. The <citetitle>Midpoint 
            Displacement Method (MPD)</citetitle> <biblioref linkend="Area51"/> 
          is, perhaps, the prototypical example of this.  
          <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> also takes a progressive 
          refinement approach, though with a bit more sophistication in how it 
          introduces new details.
        </para>
        <para>
          A main advantage of progressive refinement methods over superposition 
          methods is that they can make use of the previously constructed, 
          coarse detail in deciding where and how to introduce the new, 
          fine-scale detail.  While no previously existing method of which I am 
          aware exploits this at all (and 
          <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>, in its current incarnation, 
          does so only to a limited degree), I believe that this family of 
          methods holds the most promise for generating realistic terrain 
          containing recognizable, coherent features, such as rivers, volcanoes, 
          and ravines.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="Fractals and Not">
        <title>Fractals &amp; Non-fractals</title>
        <para>
          All terrain generation methods that are not agnostic with respect to 
          LOD must decide how to handle the different LODs: what kinds of 
          features will appear in each LOD, how large they will be, and how 
          they will relate to one another.  A physically correct solution to 
          this problem is difficult (perhaps the "Holy Grail" of terrain 
          generation), and as a result, many researchers and practitioners have 
          turned to fractals as an approximate solution.
        </para>
        <para>
          In his seminal work, <citetitle>The Fractal Geometry of 
            Nature</citetitle> <biblioref linkend="Mandelbrot"/>, Benoit 
          Mandelbrot observed that many objects in nature display the fractal 
          characteristic of <firstterm>self-similarity</firstterm>, having 
          essentially the same structure when viewed at a variety of scales.  
          For example, the small-scale variations in elevation across a 
          1-meter-square piece of mountainous terrain might,  if one zooms back 
          far enough, happen to resemble the large-scale variations across the 
          entire mountain range.  This observation has been applied to great 
          effect in computer graphics, with fractal algorithms being used as 
          reasonable approximations of a number of natural structures, both 
          regular (e.g., plants and trees) and irregular (e.g., terrain).
        </para>
        <para>
          Randomized fractal algorithms are a convenient method of creating 
          irregular shapes across an entire range of LODs. Because each 
          successively finer LOD has a defined relationship to the one 
          preceding it (modulo the effects of the random number generator), 
          fractal algorithms offer effectively unlimited amounts of detail: 
          when rendering a fractal surface, one can evaluate the fractal to 
          whatever degree of fineness the display system is able to show.
        </para>
        <para>
          Still, as useful as the fractal approximation for terrain is, it 
          cannot tell the whole story&em;not all types of terrain exhibit 
          conveniently self-similar properties across all the levels of detail 
          at which we experience them. To see that this must be the case, one 
          need only consider the diverse array of physical forces that interact 
          to create real-world terrain&em;plate tectonics, erosion due to wind 
          &amp; water, earthquakes, avalanches, floods &amp; volcanic eruptions, 
          dehydration &amp; thermal expansion (to name a few)&em;it is 
          intuitively obvious that each of these forces acts more noticeably at 
          some scales than at others.  <xref linkend="Cracked Mud"/> is a 
          photograph, taken close-up, of cracked, dried mud formed at the bottom 
          of a volcanic crater in the Death Valley area in California; if a 
          fractal relationship held between this bit of terrain and its 
          surrounding macro-environment, we would expect to find it in the 
          context of an area characterized by broad, flat mesas, separated by 
          narrow, severe ravines. As it turns out, this photo was taken at the 
          bottom of a relatively shallow, sloping crater. Obviously, in this 
          example, no fractal relationship holds between these two scales.
        </para>
        <figure id="Cracked Mud">
          <title>Cracked Mud</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              A photograph taken close-up of cracked mud. The physical process 
              predominantly responsible for this effect does not manifest in the 
              same way in the surrounding larger-scale environment. As a result, 
              while a fractal relationship does appear to exist in the terrain 
              in this photo, we would not expect this local effect to be 
              co-reducible, along with its surrounding environment, to a single 
              fractal function.  (Photo courtesy of 
              <citetitle>www.freenaturepictures.com</citetitle>.)
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata scalefit="1" width="4in"
                         fileref="Cracked Mud.jpeg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Therefore, since fractal relationships cannot be trusted to hold in 
          the general case, any terrain generation algorithm that relies on 
          fractal behavior is inherently limited&em;there will be types of 
          terrain (probably <emphasis>many</emphasis> types of terrain) that it 
          will be unable to reproduce. Any terrain generation algorithm that 
          aims to support a broad range of terrain types at various scales must 
          allow for the possibility of non-self-similar terrain.
        </para>
        <para>
          This leads to the observation that multi-scale, 
          <emphasis>fractal</emphasis> terrain generation algorithms are simply 
          a special case of a more general class of multi-scale, 
          <emphasis>not-necessarily-fractal</emphasis> terrain generation 
          algorithms. Fractal algorithms answer the question, "What should the 
          terrain look like at this scale?", with, "Just like it did at the 
          larger scale, but smaller." This is a straightforward way of 
          generating terrain across multiple LODs, but it is probably not 
          sufficient for many types of terrain.  Part of the goal of 
          <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> is to provide an alternative 
          answer to this question, leading to a terrain generation methodology 
          that is more general and controllable.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="Existing Tools">
      <title>Existing Tools for Terrain Generation</title>
      <para>
        While the list of terrain generation software is too large to be 
        reviewed exhaustively in this section, it is worthwhile to make note of 
        a representative sampling. Most of these applications permit the use of 
        more than one of the above techniques as a way of mitigating the 
        weaknesses of each.
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>Terragen</title>
        <para>
          <citetitle>Terragen</citetitle> <biblioref linkend="Terragen"/> is a 
          well-known terrain generation and rendering tool, developed by 
          Planetside Software, free for non-commercial use. It provides several 
          fractal algorithms for generating terrains and also provides a simple 
          set of sculpting tools for modifying the resultant height fields. It 
          offers an integrated ray tracing engine including some very nice 
          cloud, water, and atmospheric lighting effects, and has a significant 
          artistic community.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>MojoWorld</title>
        <para>
          <citetitle>MojoWorld</citetitle> <biblioref linkend="MojoWorld"/> is 
          a set of applications for creating and exploring fractal worlds. 
          <citetitle>MojoWorld Transporter</citetitle> is a free program for 
          exploring the worlds created by the commercial product, 
          <citetitle>MojoWorld Generator</citetitle>.  Unlike most hybrid 
          fractal/sculpting terrain generators, 
          <citetitle>MojoWorld</citetitle> handles fractal objects in symbolic 
          form, allowing entire worlds to be viewed at any level of detail and 
          stored in relatively small files.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Bryce 3D</title>
        <para>
          <citetitle>Bryce 3D</citetitle> <biblioref linkend="Bryce 3D"/> is a 
          general-purpose 3D modeling and animation tool, but is perhaps best 
          known for its terrain modeling capabilities. It offers a full set of 
          painting/sculpting tools for generating and editing 
          height-field-based terrain objects, including the ability to use Adobe 
          <citetitle>Photoshop</citetitle> image filters.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>World Machine</title>
        <para>
          <citetitle>World Machine</citetitle> <biblioref linkend="World 
            Machine"/> is a procedural height field generation tool, free for 
          non-commercial use. Its most interesting aspect is that it treats the 
          terrain creation process as composed of simple "device" primitives 
          (e.g., 2D Perlin noise generator, Gaussian blur filter, etc.) which 
          the user connects to form a "machine", a directed acyclic graph (DAG) 
          that will produce the height field when evaluated.  The main benefit 
          of this approach over a more traditional fractal/sculpting approach is 
          that, since the series of operations is preserved in the DAG, the user 
          is free to tweak the parameters of any stage of the generation 
          process, rather than having to commit to a particular filter size, 
          random seed, etc. at the outset.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Erosion 3D</title>
        <para>
          <citetitle>Erosion 3D</citetitle> <biblioref linkend="Erosion 3D"/> 
          is an application for simulating the effects of water erosion on 
          height field terrain. Developed at the Department of Soil Science and 
          Water Protection of the Institut fr Geographische Wissenschaften 
          (Institute for Geographic Sciences) in Germany, <citetitle>Erosion 
            3D</citetitle> is intended primarily as an analysis tool, not as a 
          terrain creation tool.
        </para>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="Other Terrain Sources">
      <title>Other Sources for Terrain Information</title>
      <para>
        There also exist a number of community hubs and information portals on 
        the Internet that focus partially or exclusively on the synthesis and 
        use of virtual terrain. These sites are good places to go to find 
        mature, free software, tutorials, technical specifications, and links 
        to other resources.
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>United States Geological Survey</title>
        <subtitle><ulink url="http://www.usgs.gov"/></subtitle>
        <para>
          The <citetitle>U.S. Geological Survey</citetitle> <biblioref 
            linkend="USGS"/> is a U.S.  government organization dedicated to 
          geographic, environmental and biological research. The USGS maintains 
          standards (i.e., file format specifications) for GIS data interchange, 
          offers downloadable GIS data, and provides a wealth of GIS-related 
          information.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>GeoCommunity</title>
        <subtitle><ulink url="http://www.geocomm.com"/></subtitle>
        <para>
          <citetitle>GeoCommunity</citetitle> <biblioref 
            linkend="GeoCommunity"/> is a portal site for the GIS community, 
          and provides information, software, and freely downloadable GIS data 
          for the entire United States, and some other parts of the world.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The Virtual Terrain Project</title>
        <subtitle><ulink url="http://www.vterrain.org"/></subtitle>
        <para>
          The <citetitle>Virtual Terrain Project (VTP)</citetitle> <biblioref 
            linkend="VTP"/> is an online repository containing a wealth of 
          information and free, cross-platform software, as well as a portal to 
          additional resources.  The stated goal of VTP is "to foster the 
          creation of tools for easily constructing any part of the real world 
          in interactive, 3D digital form."
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Gamasutra</title>
        <subtitle><ulink url="http://www.gamasutra.com"/></subtitle>
        <para>
          <citetitle>Gamasutra</citetitle> <biblioref linkend="Gamasutra"/> is 
          one of the premiere websites of the game developer community, 
          tracking game industry news and providing tutorials on useful 
          techniques for real-time interactive games, including techniques for 
          generating and visualizing terrain.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>NeHe</title>
        <subtitle><ulink url="http://www.nehe.gamedev.net"/></subtitle>
        <para>
          <citetitle>Neon Helium Productions (NeHe)</citetitle> <biblioref 
            linkend="NeHe"/> is another game developer community site, focused 
          on largely on OpenGL, providing articles, tutorials and sample code.  
          It has a number of tutorials on terrain rendering and generation.
        </para>
      </section>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Other Similar Works</title>
    <para>
      In the course of reviewing the existing terrain generation literature, 
      several papers were encountered that were especially similar to aspects of 
      <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> (in spirit, at least, if not in 
      application).
    </para>

    <section>
      <title><citetitle>Procedural Modeling of Cities</citetitle></title>
      <para>
        This paper <biblioref linkend="Procedural Cities"/> by Parish &amp; 
        Mller describes <citetitle>CityEngine</citetitle>, a procedural 
        approach to city generation (buildings, roads, etc.) using L-systems.  
        The user provides raster maps of the land elevation, bodies of water, 
        and population density, and <citetitle>CityEngine</citetitle> constructs 
        a plausible road network and a set of buildings matching these maps, 
        using L-system rules derived from studying actual cities.
      </para>
      <para>
        <citetitle>CityEngine</citetitle> is similar to 
        <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> in a number of ways; in fact, 
        parts of <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>'s generation pipeline 
        are inspired by that of <citetitle>CityEngine</citetitle>. In a sense, 
        they are "sister systems", attacking different problems (terrain vs.  
        cities), using different techniques (genetic algorithms vs. L-systems), 
        but with the same objective: extensible, realistic synthesis of 
        large-scale constructs, incorporating both human-designed layouts and 
        realism constraints derived from real-world observations.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><citetitle>Towards an Understanding of Landscape Scale and 
      Structure</citetitle></title>
      <para>
        This paper <biblioref linkend="Positive Wavelet"/> by Gallant &amp; 
        Hutchinson investigates the relationship between the resolution of a 
        height field and the kinds of physical features that can be detected 
        within that height field. As their analysis tool, they use a 
        <firstterm>positive wavelet decomposition</firstterm> of the height 
        field (intuitively, the inverse of the aforementioned collaging methods 
        (<xref linkend="Procedural Methods"/>), although the positive wavelet 
        decomposition does not technically have an inverse operation) to break 
        it into features of different scales, from which they draw their 
        conclusions.
      </para>
      <para>
        While their objective is quite different (they are interested in 
        hydrological analysis), their work bears a resemblance to 
        <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> in that they are seeking to 
        decompose terrain height fields into features of different scales in 
        order to characterize and understand them.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><citetitle>SAR Surface Ice Cover Discrimination Using Distribution 
      Matching</citetitle></title>
      <para>
        This paper <biblioref linkend="Ice Cover Discrimination"/> by Gill 
        describes an algorithm for computer-aided discrimination between sea 
        ice and open water from synthetic aperture radar (SAR) imagery. In this 
        algorithm, a human identifies a region he believes to be "ice" and 
        another he believes to be "water", and then the computer categorizes 
        the rest of the image as "ice" or "water" using the Kolmogorov-Smimov 
        (KS) and <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/chi^2.mml"/></inlineequation> 
        statistical distribution matching tests.
      </para>
      <para>
        This is similar to <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> in that the 
        statistical characteristics of human-identified terrain types are used 
        to compare samples of terrain for similarity, though 
        <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> uses a different means of 
        determining the degree of similarity.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><citetitle>Flexible Generation and Lightweight View-Dependent 
      Rendering of Terrain</citetitle></title>
      <para>
        This technical report <biblioref linkend="Wavelet Synthesis"/> by 
        Pelton &amp; Atkinson describes a spectral synthesis technique for 
        terrain generation based on real-world GIS example data:
      </para>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          Compute a wavelet transform of the example height field
        </step>
        <step>
          From this, construct a frequency histogram of the example height 
          field
        </step>
        <step>
          Generate a new wavelet-space representation of a height field by 
          stochastically sampling the frequency histogram from the example 
          height field
        </step>
        <step>
          Create the spatial representation of the height field by performing 
          the inverse wavelet transform
        </step>
      </procedure>
      <para>
        In this way, they are able to create new height fields similar to a 
        reference height field. They note that their approach is successful at 
        creating unique results with similar roughness characteristics to the 
        original, but that it fails to capture semantic features, specifically 
        riverbeds.
      </para>
      <para>
        Their approach is similar to <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> in 
        that both derive new, unique terrain models using example GIS elevation 
        maps.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Other Topics</title>
    <para>
      Having surveyed the landscape of terrain-related literature, there still 
      remain a few auxiliary topics that must be covered to set the stage 
      adequately for the <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> algorithm:
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          genetic algorithms
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          computer vision
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          descriptive statistics
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <section id="Genetic Algorithms Overview">
      <title>Genetic Algorithms</title>
      <para>
        Unfortunately, many of the more interesting problems in computer 
        science fall into the class of <firstterm>NP hard</firstterm> problems 
        (for which there are no known polynomial-time solutions), meaning that 
        they become intractably difficult to solve optimally as the size of the 
        problem increases <biblioref linkend="Algorithms"/>. In many cases, it 
        is not feasible to find a perfect solution, and approximation 
        techniques must be used. The <firstterm>genetic algorithm 
          (GA)</firstterm> is one of these techniques.
      </para>
      <para>
        Genetic algorithms are used in several places in 
        <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> as a way of replacing the role of 
        human intelligence with a form of artificial intelligence. By pushing 
        the burden of constructing a believable terrain model onto the 
        computer, the human user is relieved of most of the work of terrain 
        generation.
      </para>
      <para>
        Conceptually, a genetic algorithm is a parallel search algorithm that 
        tries to find better and better solutions to its problem through a 
        process analogous to the Darwinian theory of biological micro-evolution.  
        Single possible solutions within the solution space of the problem are 
        called <firstterm>chromosomes</firstterm> (or, alternatively,  
        <firstterm>individuals</firstterm>). A <firstterm>fitness 
          function</firstterm> provides an evaluation of how good of a solution 
        any particular chromosome is, expressed as a scalar value. As the GA 
        iterates, new potential solutions to the problem are explored by taking 
        the more "fit" of the existing chromosomes and recombining some of their 
        sub-parts (their <firstterm>genes</firstterm>) to create new chromosomes 
        having characteristics of both "parents". By iteratively evolving a 
        <firstterm>population</firstterm> of chromosomes (generally of some 
        fixed size), the GA explores the solution space in a parallel fashion.  
        Hopefully, after some reasonable number of iterations, the most "fit" of 
        the chromosomes in the final population will be fairly close to an 
        optimal solution to the problem <biblioref linkend="Genetic 
          Algorithms"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        In order to adapt a GA to solve a particular problem, we must define 
        three basic things:
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            a modular, genetic encoding for describing candidate solutions
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            crossover and mutation operators to work on this genetic 
            representation
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            a fitness function for evaluating the "goodness" of a particular 
            candidate solution
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        The meaning and implementation of these things will vary according to 
        the problem domain to which the GA is applied.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Computer Vision</title>
      <para>
        <firstterm>Computer vision</firstterm> is the branch of computer 
        science concerned with processing images to recover conceptual 
        representations of the objects present within those images. Computer 
        vision techniques are useful in a number of areas, especially robotics 
        and augmented reality (AR) applications.
      </para>
      <para>
        In <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>, feature detection techniques 
        are used in the analysis of terrain models, to find the location, size, 
        and scale of geometric features of the terrain (such as edges, ridges, 
        and peaks).
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>Single-scale Feature Detection</title>
        <para>
          The normal method of feature detection is to design a 
          <firstterm>detector</firstterm> for the desired feature, a function 
          that, given a pixel location within the image, returns a scalar 
          <firstterm>response</firstterm> indicating how much the pixels in that 
          vicinity resemble the desired feature. The stronger the resemblance, 
          the higher the response will be. This detector is then passed over 
          every pixel in the image, and its response recorded.  Pixels 
          containing local maxima of the detector response are kept, and the 
          other pixels are zeroed, a technique called <firstterm>non-maximal 
            suppression</firstterm>. The result is a greyscale image with grey 
          or white pixels wherever the feature was found and black elsewhere.
        </para>
        <para>
          Feature detectors are highly sensitive to the scale of the feature 
          being detected. For example, an edge detector optimized for finding 
          sharp edges between regions will perform poorly if the edges in the 
          image are diffuse (i.e., blurry), especially in the presence of noise.  
          Thus, it is important to tune the detector to the scale of feature 
          being sought.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Scale-space Feature Detection</title>
        <para>
          Unfortunately, in many computer vision applications, the scales at 
          which features will appear are unknown.  If this is the case, then 
          <firstterm>scale-space</firstterm> feature detection may be used to 
          search for features across a range of scales <biblioref 
            linkend="Scale-space Blob"/> <biblioref linkend="Scale-space 
            Edge/Ridge"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Scale-space feature detection is a relatively straightforward 
          extension of single-scale feature detection, in which locally maximal 
          detector responses are looked for, not only across the 
          <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/(x,y).mml"/></inlineequation> domain of the image, 
          but also across adjacent scales.  Because the algorithm is independent 
          of the actual feature detector matrix used, virtually any single-scale 
          detector may be adapted to work in scale-space, including "blob" 
          detectors, "edge" detectors, "ridge" detectors, etc.
        </para>
        <procedure>
          <para>
            The major steps in scale-space feature detection are:
          </para>
          <step>
            Generate the scale-space representation of the image by convolving 
            the image with successively larger Gaussian blobs. This produces a 
            3-dimensional image "cube", in which the added dimension represents 
            scale; as the scale parameter increases, fine-scale image details 
            disappear, leaving only the larger-scale shapes.
          </step>
          <step>
            Calculate the feature detector response at every pixel in the 
            scale-space image.
          </step>
          <step>
            Find the locations within the scale-space image at which the 
            detector response is maximal. Finding the maxima in the 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/x.mml"/></inlineequation> and             
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/y.mml"/></inlineequation> dimensions yields the 
            locations of the detected features, while finding the scale at which 
            each is maximized gives an estimate of the size of the feature.
          </step>
        </procedure>
        <para>
          In this way, features present in the image may be recovered and, 
          additionally, classified according to the scale at which they appear.  
          For example, when ridge detection is performed on an image of a 
          crumpled piece of cloth, a tiny wrinkle in the fabric will yield a 
          maximal detector response at a fine scale, and will completely 
          disappear as the scale is increased. In contrast, a gentle fold in the 
          fabric will give some small response at the finest scale, and a much 
          higher response as the scale approaches that of the fold.
        </para>
        <para>
          If the only benefit of scale-space detectors over single-scale 
          detectors were that features are detectable at multiple scales, this 
          would not be much of an improvement over single-scale detectors 
          (since the same thing can be accomplished by running a single-scale 
          detector multiple times, at several different scales), and not worth 
          the additional cost in memory and computation time.  However, since 
          scale-space detectors are able to examine multiple scales 
          <emphasis>simultaneously</emphasis>, a "long" feature (such as an edge 
          or ridge) can be recognized as a single feature, even if it varies 
          dramatically in scale along its length. In contrast, a multi-pass, 
          single-scale detector would register multiple, partially overlapping 
          features in this case, rather than a single feature of varying scale.  
          As a result, a scale-space detector will report fewer features (and 
          generally, more meaningful ones).
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="Descriptive Statistics">
      <title>Descriptive Statistics</title>
      <para>
        <firstterm>Descriptive statistics</firstterm> is the branch of 
        statistics dealing with identifying patterns and trends within 
        collected samples of data. In <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>, 
        measured statistics are used as a basis for comparing terrains for 
        similarity: intuitively, the more similar the statistical 
        characteristics of two terrains, the more "alike" they are. In 
        particular, we are interested in the following four statistics:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>the sample mean</listitem>
        <listitem>the sample standard deviation</listitem>
        <listitem>the sample skewness</listitem>
        <listitem>the sample kurtosis excess</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The following diagrams of these statistics depict distributions similar 
        in shape to a Gaussian (normal) distribution.  This is because some of 
        these measures (the skewness and kurtosis excess) are defined with 
        reference to the Gaussian distribution, such that the Gaussian 
        distribution has a value of zero. Thus, Gaussian-like distributions are 
        convenient for conveying an intuitive sense of the statistic.  This 
        should not be taken to mean that these measures apply only to the 
        Gaussian distribution; they are defined wholly in terms of raw moments 
        and central moments of the distribution, and can be applied to any 
        distribution. The degree to which these measures deviate from zero gives 
        an indication of how non-Gaussian the distribution is.
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>The Sample Mean</title>
        <para>
          The best-known statistic is the <firstterm>sample mean</firstterm>, or 
          unweighted average (<xref linkend="Sample Mean Equation"/>).  
          Intuitively, this is the "center" value of a sample distribution 
          (<xref linkend="Mean Illustration"/>) <biblioref linkend="Mean"/>.
        </para>
        <figure id="Mean Illustration">
          <title>Mean</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              The mean of a statistical distribution is a first-order measure 
              and is the value around which the distribution is centered.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Statistics - Mean Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <equation id="Sample Mean Equation">
          <title>The Sample Mean</title>
          <xi:include href="resources/Statistics - Sample Mean Equation.mml"/>
        </equation>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The Sample Standard Deviation</title>
        <para>
          A second useful statistic is the <firstterm>sample standard 
          deviation</firstterm>, <inlineequation><xi:include 
          href="resources/sigma.mml"/></inlineequation>, a non-negative value 
          measuring the degree of variability of a sample distribution (<xref 
          linkend="Sample Standard Deviation Equation"/>). A low standard 
          deviation indicates that the sample values are tightly clustered about 
          the mean (<xref linkend="Standard Deviation Illustration"/>) 
          <biblioref linkend="Standard Deviation"/>.
        </para>
        <figure id="Standard Deviation Illustration">
          <title>Standard Deviation</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              The standard deviation of a statistical distribution is a 
              second-order measure describing the degree to which the 
              distribution is "spread out".
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Statistics - Standard Deviation Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <equation id="Sample Standard Deviation Equation">
          <title>The Sample Standard Deviation</title>
          <xi:include href="resources/Statistics - Sample Standard Deviation Equation.mml"/>
        </equation>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The Sample Skewness</title>
        <para>
          A third, lesser-known statistic is the <firstterm>sample 
            skewness</firstterm>, <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/gamma_1.mml"/></inlineequation>, which measures 
          the degree of asymmetry of a sample distribution (<xref 
            linkend="Sample Skewness Equation"/>). A skewness of zero indicates 
          that the distribution is perfectly symmetrical about the  mean, 
          whereas a positive or negative skewness indicates that the 
          distribution is skewed to the left or right of the mean, respectively 
          (<xref linkend="Skewness Illustration"/>) <biblioref 
            linkend="Skewness"/>.
        </para>
        <figure id="Skewness Illustration">
          <title>Skewness</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              The skewness of a statistical distribution is a third-order 
              measure describing the amount of asymmetry of the distribution.  
              Values less than zero indicate that the distribution is skewed to 
              the left of the mean, and values greater than zero indicate that 
              the distribution is skewed to the right.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Statistics - Skewness Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <equation id="Sample Skewness Equation">
          <title>The Sample Skewness</title>
          <xi:include href="resources/Statistics - Sample Skewness Equation.mml"/>
        </equation>
        <para>
          This formulation of the skewness is in terms of the second and third 
          <firstterm>k-statistics</firstterm>. The first four k-statistics are 
          given in <xref linkend="k-Statistic Equations"/> <biblioref 
          linkend="k-Statistic"/>.
        </para>
        <equation id="k-Statistic Equations">
          <title>The First Four k-Statistics</title>
          <xi:include href="resources/Statistics - K-statistic Equations.mml"/>
        </equation>
        <para>
          where <inlineequation><xi:include 
          href="resources/_n.mml"/></inlineequation> is the sample size and the 
          <inlineequation><xi:include 
          href="resources/m_r.mml"/></inlineequation>'s are the 
          <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/_r.mml"/></inlineequation>
          <superscript>th</superscript> sample central moments, given by <xref 
          linkend="Sample Central Moment Equation"/> <biblioref linkend="Sample 
          Central Moment"/>.
        </para>
        <equation id="Sample Central Moment Equation">
          <title>Sample Central Moment</title>
          <xi:include href="resources/Statistics - Sample Central Moment Equation.mml"/>
        </equation>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The Sample Kurtosis Excess</title>
        <para>
          A fourth statistic is the <firstterm>sample kurtosis 
          excess</firstterm>, <inlineequation><xi:include 
          href="resources/gamma_2.mml"/></inlineequation>, often simply called 
          the <firstterm>sample kurtosis</firstterm>, which measures the degree 
          of peakedness of a sample distribution (<xref linkend="Sample Kurtosis 
            Equation"/>).  The normal distribution has a kurtosis of zero, 
          whereas a more peaked distribution  has a positive kurtosis and a 
          flattened distribution has a negative kurtosis (<xref 
            linkend="Kurtosis Illustration"/>) <biblioref linkend="Kurtosis"/>.
        </para>
        <figure id="Kurtosis Illustration">
          <title>Kurtosis</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              The kurtosis excess of a statistical distribution is a 
              fourth-order measure describing the amount of "peakedness" of the 
              distribution. Values less than zero indicate that the distribution 
              is more "flat" than a normal distribution, and values greater than 
              zero indicate that the distribution is more peaked than a normal 
              distribution.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Statistics - Kurtosis Excess Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <equation id="Sample Kurtosis Equation">
          <title>The Sample Kurtosis Excess</title>
          <xi:include href="resources/Statistics - Sample Kurtosis Excess Equation.mml"/>
        </equation>
      </section>
      <para>
        The <inlineequation><xi:include 
        href="resources/k_i.mml"/></inlineequation>'s are the second and fourth 
        k-statistics, as defined above in <xref linkend="k-Statistic 
        Equations"/>.
      </para>
    </section>

  </section>

</chapter>
