<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!-- vim: set filetype=docbkxml encoding=utf8: -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//JediRy//DTD DocBook XML-MathML-SVG V4.3//EN"
  "http://jediry.com/xml/docbook/docbook4.3-mathml-svg.dtd">


<chapter id="Methods">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <para>
    In this chapter, I discuss the <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> 
    algorithm at a conceptual level, including its overall strategy and major 
    steps, explaining the rationale for important design decisions. The gritty 
    details of implementing the algorithm are glossed over here, and presented 
    in detail in the chapter on implementation (<xref 
    linkend="Implementation"/>). These topics will be covered in the following 
    order:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      prerequisites&em;design strategy and basic tools
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      how the algorithm works from the user's perspective
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      how the algorithm works from the computer's perspective
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <para>
      Before delving into the details of the algorithm, there are several 
      things that must be nailed down first, outlining the basic strategies 
      underlying <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        how ease of use will be ensured
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        how the terrain generation problem will be attacked
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        what data structure will be used to represent the terrain
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        how level of detail will be addressed
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Usability Considerations</title>
      <para>
        Since one of our major stated objectives is to create something easy to 
        use, this aspect deserves specific consideration. While a full-scale 
        user study would be helpful in this respect, this is outside the scope 
        of this thesis. Nevertheless, there are basic user-interaction decisions 
        we can make that will, <foreignphrase>prima facie</foreignphrase>, 
        promote usability.
      </para>
      <para>
        The crucial observation to make, in this regard, is that not all 
        possible parameters and constraints for a terrain generation algorithm 
        are of the same nature. For our purposes, it will suffice to 
        distinguish between three types:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          those that are essentially <firstterm>free</firstterm>, meaning that 
          the user can manipulate them for artistic purposes (within limits, of 
          course), without damaging the apparent realism of the 
          terrain&em;examples of these include the size of a mountain range, 
          and the placement of lakes and mountain peaks
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          those that are critical for maintaining the apparent realism of the 
          terrain&em;examples of these include the characteristic fine-scale 
          detail of different terrain types, and the smoothness of transitions 
          between different terrain types
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          everything else&em;the miscellaneous parameters that influence things 
          like algorithm running time, memory usage and quality of results
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        In everything, our goal is for <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> to 
        be thoroughly intuitive. For each of these three types of 
        parameters/constraints, a different method of user interaction is most 
        appropriate.
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>Visual Authoring</title>
        <para>
          Those aspects of the terrain that can be freely manipulated for 
          artistic effect without impacting the realism of the terrain belong 
          under the control of the user. Since most of these are spatial and/or 
          visual, a visual authoring environment is the obvious choice, allowing 
          the author to interact with a visual representation of his work, and 
          to refine it incrementally until it reaches his satisfaction. Human 
          beings process visually-presented information quite efficiently, and 
          we would expect this to be especially true of information that is 
          already spatial in nature, such as terrain.  Furthermore, the digital 
          art community works almost exclusively with 2D and 3D visual authoring 
          tools (e.g., <citetitle>Photoshop</citetitle>, <citetitle>3D 
            Studio</citetitle>, <citetitle>Maya</citetitle>), and will be much 
          more likely to adopt a tool that allows them to work in this fashion.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Example-based Design</title>
        <para>
          In contrast to the previous section, those aspects of the terrain that 
          are crucial for maintaining its realism are not especially suitable 
          candidates for user authoring. These are likely to be more highly 
          constrained, and possibly in ways that are not well understood or 
          would be tedious or impossible to replicate by hand (e.g., satisfying 
          a certain statistical distribution). Such things are perhaps better 
          left for the computer to solve, freeing the user to do what the 
          computer cannot: imagine and create.
        </para>
        <para>
          Still, the user needs to be able to control the characteristics of 
          the generated terrain in <emphasis>some</emphasis> way.  A 
          <firstterm>design by example</firstterm> approach is a graceful 
          method of specifying these characteristics: rather than requiring the 
          user to comprehend the complexities that give a particular flavor of 
          terrain its identity, we simply ask him to provide one or more 
          examples that exhibit the characteristics he would like to see 
          replicated in his terrain. In this way, the burden of 
          reverse-engineering terrain is transferred off of the user and on to 
          the software, and the algorithm becomes a true "black box" from the 
          user's perspective, requiring almost no domain knowledge to be used.
        </para>
        <para>
          Two additional benefits come from taking such an approach. First, the 
          algorithm is easily extensible, since the user can simply add new 
          examples of terrain to achieve new effects. Second, the algorithm can 
          be "upgraded" completely transparently to the user&em;because of the 
          simplicity of the interface, improvements can be made to the algorithm 
          without the user having to learn to use new parameters, or even 
          needing to know that anything has changed.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Miscellaneous Controls</title>
        <para>
          Naturally, there are other parameters and constraints that do not fit 
          well into either of the above categories.  If these values cannot be 
          determined automatically, then other methods of presenting them to 
          the user will be required, such as standard GUI controls (sliders, 
          buttons, etc.).
        </para>
        <para>
          Having additional, non-visual parameters for the user to set is not, 
          in itself, a problem.  The important thing is not for all parameters 
          to be expressible visually, but for all parameters to be 
          <emphasis>intuitive</emphasis>: the meaning of the parameter should 
          be easily understood by a user who has no comprehension of the inner 
          workings of the algorithm. As a result, the user should have a fair 
          idea of what the effect of changing each parameter will be, even 
          before the change is made.
        </para>
        <para>
          One example of a non-visual parameter that is nonetheless intuitive 
          is a "quality" parameter that adjusts a tradeoff between the amount 
          of processing time spent and the realism of the result produced. Even 
          though this tradeoff does not have an obvious visual meaning, humans 
          already understand the concept of spending additional time working on 
          a task to achieve a better result.
        </para>
        <para>
          As an example of the sort of parameters that we want to 
          <emphasis>avoid</emphasis> presenting to the user, consider the 
          well-known Perlin Noise <biblioref linkend="Perlin Noise"/> function.  
          While the usefulness of Perlin Noise is indisputable&em;it has been 
          used to great effect for creating believable imitations of a wide 
          variety of natural phenomena&em;it has a significant drawback: it 
          requires a non-trivial amount of domain knowledge (or else brute 
          force, trial-and-error experimentation) to achieve a desired result.  
          To a novice user, the parameters (e.g., <property>octaves</property>, 
          <property>turbulence</property>, <property>persistence</property>) are 
          "magic": it is difficult to gain an intuition for the effects of 
          tweaking one of them without first understanding how Perlin Noise 
          works.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Terrain Generation Strategy</title>
      <para>
        Obviously, there is no unique "correct" answer to the problem of 
        generating terrain; instead, there are infinitely many "good" answers, 
        infinitely many more "bad" answers, and everything in between. Thus, 
        the quest to make believable terrain can be viewed as a search over an 
        infinitely large solution space, in which some solutions are 
        quantitatively better than others.
      </para>
      <para>
        A number of methods exist for finding good approximate solutions to 
        problems for which an exhaustive search is infeasible or (as in the 
        case of terrain generation) impossible. These methods vary in 
        performance and generality. In <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>, 
        we have chosen to use a genetic algorithm for this purpose (<xref 
          linkend="Genetic Algorithms"/>). The major benefits of GAs (for our 
        purposes) are:
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            they are randomized, rather than deterministic; as a result, they 
            are capable of some degree of innovation and can produce an 
            effectively unlimited number of unique terrain models.  
            Additionally, this randomness can enable a properly-tuned GA to 
            escape from locally "best" solutions in order to find other, better 
            solutions.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            they are extremely general: a GA treats its problem as a "black 
            box", and need not understand the complex effects of the changes it 
            makes, only caring about the results of the fitness evaluation.  
            Because of this, a GA can unite a diversity of orthogonal or 
            competing constraints: anything that can be incorporated into the 
            fitness evaluation. This makes a GA an attractive development tool, 
            as it leaves open a straightforward means of adding new constraints 
            as they become necessary.
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Choice of Data Structure</title>
      <para>
        The terrain data structure used in 
        <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> is the height field
        <footnote>
          <para>
            Throughout the remainder of this thesis, the terms <firstterm>height 
            field</firstterm> and <firstterm>terrain</firstterm> will be used 
            synonymously, unless otherwise noted.
          </para>
        </footnote>
        (<xref linkend="Height Fields"/>). This decision makes sense in light of 
        two facts:
      </para>
      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          most current, real-time applications of terrain use height fields
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          GIS elevation data is most widely available in this form; as a result, 
          the data has <emphasis>already</emphasis> been sampled to a finite 
          resolution and has lost its ability to resolve features like overhangs 
          and caves. Thus, there is no further penalty for using height fields, 
          and no additional benefit to using other representations that do not 
          share these restrictions
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Level of Detail Strategy</title>
      <para>
        From an LOD perspective, the terrain generation problem can be 
        understood as the problem of constructing a height field having the 
        following characteristics:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          at each LOD, appropriate, characteristic features are present in the 
          terrain, in correct proportions
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          the entire set of LODs is <firstterm>coherent</firstterm>, meaning 
          that features present in coarse LODs continue to exist at the same 
          locations in the finer LODs
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        As was stated in <xref linkend="Progressive Refinement Methods"/>, 
        <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> approaches terrain construction as 
        a multi-LOD, progressive refinement process. As was also mentioned 
        earlier (<xref linkend="Fractals and Not"/>), one of the more 
        significant goals of <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> is to offer a 
        not-necessarily-fractal answer to the question of what the terrain ought 
        to look like at any given LOD.
      </para>
    </section>
    
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The User's Perspective (What It Does)</title>
    <para>
      Since ease-of-use is one of the primary objectives of our approach, it is 
      worth taking some time to walk through how our approach looks from the 
      perspective of a user. This will also serve to create the context for the 
      more technical discussion to follow. Consider a hypothetical user, a set 
      designer for a large computer animation studio. Among this user's routine 
      tasks is the construction of outdoor, virtual worlds for the commercials, 
      feature films, and video game content that his company develops.
    </para>
    <para>
      From the user's perspective, terrain generation with       
      <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> involves three discrete phases:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        assembling a terrain library
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        authoring a terrain map
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        generating a height field
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section id="Terrain Library Assembly">
      <title>Terrain Library Assembly</title>
      <para>
        The user's first step is to assemble a <firstterm>terrain 
          library</firstterm>, the "palette" with which he will later "paint" 
        his terrain models. His task in this phase is to define the taxonomy of 
        <firstterm>terrain types</firstterm> he wants to use.  Terrain types are  
        logical abstractions, semantic classes of terrain, as a human would 
        think of them (things like "steep mountains", "sandy beach", "rocky 
        desert", "plains", etc.) and are created by providing one or more 
        <firstterm>terrain samples</firstterm>, example height fields 
        representative of these classes. These examples will normally come from 
        providers of real-world GIS data (e.g., <biblioref 
          linkend="GeoCommunity"/>), though they could potentially come from 
        other sources as well. Once the user has populated his library with 
        example terrains, <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> analyzes the 
        library (see <xref linkend="Terrain Library Analysis"/>) in order to 
        identify unifying characteristics for each terrain type, measurable 
        quantities that are similar across all of the example terrains within a 
        single terrain type (and thus, which are likely to contribute to the 
        user's perception of those terrains as being related). These example 
        terrains will also serve as the raw material for constructing new height 
        fields in the third phase (see <xref linkend="Height Field GA"/>).
      </para>
      <para>
        Because terrain types are correlative to human mental categories, they 
        are effectively unlimited in number, and will vary according to the 
        user.  No matter how many terrain types are identified, there will 
        always be someone who wants something just a bit different. At the same 
        time, the choice of terrain types is not wholly arbitrary&em;it is 
        important that example terrains for the same terrain type 
        <emphasis>are</emphasis> truly similar in some way, or else the terrain 
        analysis process will be hindered, because 
        <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> will be unable to identify 
        meaningful unifying characteristics for that terrain type.
      </para>
      <para>
        The user's terrain libraries can be as coarse- or as fine-grained as he 
        wishes, depending on his needs, and he might have separate libraries for 
        different purposes. For example, he might define many variations of 
        "mountains" in order to finely control the kinds of features that appear 
        throughout a mountainous terrain model, or he might have only a few, 
        highly different, general-purpose terrain types for building more 
        heterogeneous worlds.
      </para>
      <para>
        While the construction of the terrain library is likely to be a bit 
        tedious, it is something that will be done only infrequently, as once a 
        terrain library has been assembled, it can be reused indefinitely, and 
        extended incrementally as additional terrain types are needed. <xref 
          linkend="Computer-aided Classification"/> discusses potential avenues 
        for future research that might help alleviate this burden on the user.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Map Design</title>
      <para>
        The user's primary design task when using 
        <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> is to create the layout of his 
        terrain. He does this visually, creating a 2D, vector-drawn map of the 
        terrain using a CAD-style interface (<xref linkend="Map Editor 
          Interface"/>).  By representing the map as a vector drawing rather 
        than a raster image, we avoid committing to a particular resolution for 
        the map, enabling the user to defer the decision of what LOD to generate 
        until he actually generates it, allowing him to produce multiple LODs 
        from a single map.  The map is made up of one or more polygonal regions 
        of terrain, which may be of arbitrary sizes and shapes. Each region is 
        assigned one of the terrain types from the library. Through sketching 
        out such regions and tweaking their shapes, the user can express the 
        approximate layout he desires for his terrain, using a modeling paradigm 
        that is well-established and intuitive.
      </para>
      <figure id="Map Editor Interface">
        <title>The Map Authoring Interface</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <caption>
            The user describes his desired terrain layout by authoring a 2D map, 
            which specifies the location, size, and shape of regions of terrain, 
            each of which may have its own terrain type.  A CAD-style interface 
            allows the user to accomplish this using a familiar and intuitive 
            design paradigm.
          </caption>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata scalefit="1" width="4in"
                       fileref="Map Authoring Interface.jpeg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <section>
        <title>Boundary Refinement</title>
        <para>
          The use of polygons to represent regions in the terrain type map has 
          the advantage of simplicity: operations on polygons are well-defined 
          and well-understood, and provide a straightforward way for a user to 
          work with the map.  However, while linear shapes are useful tools for 
          modeling, their linearity is also a drawback: since polygons are 
          restricted to having straight edges, curved or irregular shapes may 
          require large numbers of small segments to be adequately approximated.  
          If the approximation is not fine enough for the particular 
          application, the unrealistically straight edges will be visible. In 
          our case, this means that if the length of a linear region boundary is 
          large compared to the resolution of the generated height field, this 
          boundary may be reflected visibly in the generated terrain as an 
          unnaturally straight transition between two terrain  types; the longer 
          the boundary, the more noticeable this is likely to be.  If the height 
          field is colored or texture-mapped according to terrain type, this 
          effect is greatly magnified (<xref linkend="Boundary Artifacts"/>).  
          Therefore it is important that the boundaries between regions be of 
          sufficiently fine scale.
        </para>
        <figure id="Boundary Artifacts">
          <title>Artifacts Resulting from Linear Region Boundaries</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              Seams between adjacent regions can appear as unnatural-looking 
              artifacts in the generated height field if the region boundaries 
              are long and linear. This effect is made all the more obvious by 
              coloring or texture-mapping the regions.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata scalefit="1" width="4in"
                         fileref="Height Field With Boundary Artifacts.jpeg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Creating such fine-scale boundaries by hand would be quite tedious, 
          and it is much to be preferred, from a user-experience standpoint, 
          that this task be automated. We do this by providing a 
          <firstterm>boundary refinement</firstterm> operation, which 
          non-destructively replaces a straight boundary from the user's 
          polygonal map with a new boundary that follows the same approximate 
          path as the original, but with a meandering, irregular shape made up 
          of many short segments (<xref linkend="Boundary Refinement"/>). The 
          user influences the shape of this boundary by adjusting a 
          <firstterm>smoothness</firstterm> parameter. The resulting 
          <firstterm>refined boundary</firstterm> will be used instead of the 
          original linear boundary when the height field is constructed, 
          producing a more believable, irregular transition between the regions 
          (<xref linkend="Artifact-free Boundary"/>). The gory details of this 
          operation are described later, in <xref linkend="Boundary GA"/>.  
          Using this operation, the user is enabled to sketch his map using 
          rough, simple shapes, and then to fill in fine-scale boundary detail 
          automatically.  With this paradigm, even an inexperienced user should 
          be able to create a simple but believable map in just a few minutes.
        </para>
        <figure id="Boundary Refinement">
          <title>The Boundary Refinement Operation</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              The boundary refinement operation replaces a long, linear segment 
              of a region boundary with a string of short segments connecting 
              the same endpoints.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Boundary Refinement.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure id="Artifact-free Boundary">
          <title>A Refined Boundary Avoids Unnatural-looking Artifacts</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              With long, linear boundaries replaced by irregular, meandering 
              boundaries, such boundary artifacts are no longer evident in the 
              generated height field.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata scalefit="1" width="4in"
                         fileref="Height Field Without Boundary Artifacts.jpeg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Height Field Construction</title>
      <para>
        Once satisfied with the map he has created, the user selects a 
        rectangular chunk of the map, chooses the desired level of detail, and 
        launches the height field generation algorithm. This third phase of the 
        process is computationally expensive (and therefore, slow), but is also 
        entirely automated: once started, no further input from the user is 
        needed, and he can go on to other tasks.
      </para>
      <para>
        In this phase, <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> generates a height 
        field at multiple LODs, beginning from the coarsest possible LOD and 
        continuing up to the target LOD requested by the user.  At each LOD, the 
        height field is built such that the features present in each region 
        resemble those of the corresponding terrain types at that LOD.
      </para>
      <para>
        A secondary, optional by-product of generating each LOD is a rasterized 
        version  of the user's map, an image file with the same raster 
        dimensions as the generated height field, in which each pixel represents 
        the terrain type of the corresponding grid cell in the height field.  
        This information could be loaded and used by another program to do 
        terrain-type-based postprocessing, such as generating a texture map for 
        the height field, or simulating erosion of the terrain surface using 
        terrain-type-specific soil characteristics.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="The Computer's Perspective">
    <title>The Computer's Perspective (How It Works)</title>
    <para>
      Having covered the fundamental concepts in 
      <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> and outlined the general steps of 
      the algorithm, all that remains to be done is to peer inside of the "black 
      boxes" in the above outline, and fill in the details.  In this section, I 
      discuss the following aspects:
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          the boundary refinement algorithm
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          height field analysis &amp; comparison
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          the height field generation algorithm
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <section id="Boundary GA">
      <title>Boundary Refinement</title>
      <para>
        The boundary refinement operation is the first algorithmic aspect of 
        <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> that I discuss, and also the first 
        problem that we solve using a genetic algorithm.
      </para>

      <section id="Boundary GA Overview">
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>
          The boundary refinement operation is essentially a randomized 
          subdivision operation. It takes as input a single line segment of 
          arbitrary length and produces a piecewise-linear curve with the same 
          starting and ending points as the original segment, but made up of 
          <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/N.mml"/></inlineequation> 
          segments (connecting <inlineequation><xi:include 
          href="resources/N+1.mml"/></inlineequation> points), where
          <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/N.mml"/></inlineequation> is 
          proportional to the length of the original segment. This curve is then 
          translated, rotated and scaled as needed to line it up with the 
          original boundary's end points. Since we will ultimately be 
          transforming the entire curve anyway, we can, without loss of 
          generality, think of the original boundary as lying along the positive 
          <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/x.mml"/></inlineequation> 
          axis, starting from the origin. All of the diagrams in this section 
          reflect this convention.
        </para>
        <para>
          A useful result of applying this operation to each boundary in the 
          map is that the segment length throughout the entire map is roughly 
          uniform (recall that <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/N.mml"/></inlineequation>, the number of segments, 
          was said to be proportional to the length of the original boundary).  
          If this length is chosen to be small enough, relative to the 
          resolution of the height field that will be generated, no straight 
          boundaries between terrain types will be evident in the generated 
          height field, nor in any texture maps applied to the height field.
        </para>
        <para>
          The segment length (and thus, the number of segments) may be 
          calculated from the resolution of the target height field, according 
          to the spatial version of the Nyquist limit: considering the height 
          field as sampling the boundary, we know that the height field cannot 
          resolve boundary details finer than half its spatial resolution 
          (<xref linkend="Nyquist Equation"/>).
        </para>
        <equation id="Nyquist Equation">
          <title>The Maximum Segment Length, Set According to the Nyquist 
          Limit</title>
          <xi:include href="resources/Boundary GA - Nyquist Equation.mml"/>
        </equation>
        <para>
          However, since the generated boundary may need to be scaled somewhat 
          to match the endpoints of the original boundary, we incorporate a 
          "slop factor" of two, resulting in <xref linkend="Boundary Segment 
            Length Equation"/>.
        </para>
        <equation id="Boundary Segment Length Equation">
          <title>Maximum Boundary Segment Length</title>
          <xi:include href="resources/Boundary GA - Segment Length Equation.mml"/>
        </equation>
        <para>
          The shape of the generated boundary is subject to the constraints 
          imposed by the user. The user can control how sharp the angles between 
          successive segments are allowed to be by adjusting the 
          <firstterm>smoothness</firstterm> parameter,
          <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/S.mml"/></inlineequation>, which can 
          vary from 0.0 (very rough) to 1.0 (very smooth).
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="Boundary GA Encoding">
        <title>Genetic Encoding</title>
        <para>
          The first step in casting the boundary refinement problem as a 
          genetic algorithm is to define a suitable genetic encoding for a 
          boundary. In the encoding we selected, a chromosome has
          <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/N.mml"/></inlineequation>
          genes, one for each segment in the resulting boundary, and each gene 
          contains a real-valued angle in the range <inlineequation><xi:include 
          href="resources/%5B-pi,pi%5D.mml"/></inlineequation> indicating the 
          <emphasis>relative</emphasis> change in direction of the corresponding 
          segment with respect to the one preceding it (<xref linkend="Boundary 
          GA Encoding Illustration"/>). A positive angle indicates a turn to the 
          counter-clockwise direction, while a negative angle indicates a turn 
          to the clockwise direction.  A differential angle of zero indicates 
          that the segment is traveling in the same direction as the previous 
          segment. The angle of the first segment is defined with respect to the 
          <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/x.mml"/></inlineequation> 
          axis, since it has no preceding segment.
        </para>
        <figure id="Boundary GA Encoding Illustration">
          <title>The Encoding of a Gene in the Boundary GA</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              A boundary's genetic encoding is the sequence of relative angles 
              between successive segments. An angle of zero indicates no change 
              in direction.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Boundary GA - Gene Angle Encoding Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          An encoding such as this is advantageous in that it represents the 
          shape of the boundary in terms of a <emphasis>local</emphasis> 
          property of the curve (the differential angle). This is a convenient 
          representation, since the property that we are trying to optimize 
          (the curve smoothness) is itself a local property. Furthermore, the 
          curve smoothness can be calculated using only the angles, without the 
          need to convert to Cartesian coordinates, with the result that the 
          fitness evaluation can be done quite cheaply, in terms of processing 
          time.
        </para>
        <para>
          Another important consequence of this encoding is that the 
          relationship between the gene angle values and the 2D Cartesian 
          points to which they are decoded depends <emphasis>on the entire 
            chromosome</emphasis>: since each angle encoded in a gene is 
          specified relative to the preceding line segment, a change in the 
          angle of one gene will affect the location of not just the next 
          point, but of <emphasis>every</emphasis> subsequent point. As a 
          result, the end point of the boundary cannot easily be held fixed, 
          since mutations earlier in the sequence will tend to move it. This is 
          one reason that we must transform the curve at the end of the 
          algorithm, rather than simply constructing the curve "in place".
        </para>
        <para>
          A downside to this encoding is that it is possible for the boundary 
          to double back on itself, which causes several problems. We prevent 
          this by requiring that the <emphasis>absolute</emphasis> angle (i.e., 
          the angle with respect to the <inlineequation><xi:include 
          href="resources/x.mml"/></inlineequation> axis) cannot exceed a 
          certain maximum angle at any point on the boundary (<xref 
          linkend="Boundary GA Angle Limit Illustration"/>).  This is discussed 
          in more detail in <xref linkend="Boundary GA Discussion"/>.
        </para>
        <figure id="Boundary GA Angle Limit Illustration">
          <title>The Absolute Angle Limit</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              A constraint is placed on the maximum absolute angle that a 
              segment can have with respect to the reference axis, in order to 
              prevent the boundary from doubling back and intersecting with 
              itself.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Boundary GA - Angle Limit Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
          
      <section id="Boundary GA Operators">
        <title>Genetic Operators</title>
        <para>
          To mutate and cross-breed the chromosomes, we use the standard GA 
          crossover and mutation operators. Mutating a gene corresponds to 
          changing the degree of "bend" between two consecutive segments (<xref 
            linkend="Boundary GA Mutation Illustration"/>).
        </para>
        <figure id="Boundary GA Mutation Illustration">
          <title>The Boundary GA Mutation Operator</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <caption>
              Mutation of a boundary segment's gene changes the amount of "bend" 
              between that segment and its predecessor.
            </caption>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Boundary GA - Mutation Operator Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Crossing two chromosomes is the equivalent of cutting each boundary 
          in the middle of one of the segments and exchanging the pieces (<xref 
            linkend="Boundary GA Crossover Illustration"/>).
        </para>
        <figure id="Boundary GA Crossover Illustration">
          <title>The Boundary GA Crossover Operator</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Boundary GA - Crossover Operator Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section id="Boundary GA Fitness">
        <title>Fitness Evaluation</title>
        <para>
          A chromosome is "fit" if the boundary curve it represents satisfies 
          the smoothness constraint placed on it. The smoothness of a single 
          gene is calculated according to <xref linkend="Boundary GA Gene 
          Smoothness Equation"/>. When <inlineequation><xi:include 
          href="resources/S.mml"/></inlineequation> is near 1, this equation is 
          linear, favoring angles near zero and penalizing sharper angles. For 
          lower values of <inlineequation><xi:include 
          href="resources/S.mml"/></inlineequation>, the equation becomes more 
          sinusoidal, favoring sharper angles (<xref linkend="Boundary GA Gene 
          Smoothness Graph"/>). The constant 1.1 in this equation controls the 
          horizontal offset of the sinusoid's peak, and is somewhat arbitrary.
        </para>
        <equation id="Boundary GA Gene Smoothness Equation">
          <title>Boundary GA Gene Smoothness Equation</title>
          <xi:include href="resources/Boundary GA - Smoothness Equation.mml"/>
        </equation>
        <figure id="Boundary GA Gene Smoothness Graph">
          <title>The Smoothness Fitness Function for Several Values of 
          S</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Boundary GA - Smoothness Graph.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          The fitness of the entire chromosome is then calculated as the mean 
          fitness across all of the genes.
        </para>
        <!--
          The smoothness of the curve at several levels of detail, and average 
          the results to get the overall smoothness value, in order to ensure 
          that the curve is well-behaved.
        </para>
        <para>
          Calculating the fitness XXX
          The fitness at coarser LODs is calculated similarly, but rather than 
          using the angles in the genes directly, we average two or more 
          consecutive
        </para-->
      </section>

      <section id="Boundary GA Decoding">
        <title>Decoding the Result</title>
        <para>
          Once the GA has completed, we have a "best" boundary, encoded as a 
          series of floating-point, relative angle values. The final step in 
          this operation is to decode this chromosome into a series of 2D 
          points (<inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/P_0.mml"/></inlineequation> 
          to <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/P_N.mml"/></inlineequation>) 
          connecting the end points of the original boundary. This is done in a 
          relatively straightforward manner:
        </para>
        <procedure>
          <step>
            The initial point <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/P_0.mml"/></inlineequation> is placed at the origin.
          </step>
          <step>
            Subsequent points <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/P_1.mml"/></inlineequation> to 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/P_N.mml"/></inlineequation> are calculated from the 
            previous point, using the recurrence relation <xref 
            linkend="Boundary GA Point Decoding Equation"/>.
            <equation id="Boundary GA Point Decoding Equation">
              <title>Point Decoding Equation</title>
              <xi:include href="resources/Boundary GA - Point Decoding Equation.mml"/>
            </equation>
          </step>
          <step>
            The end points of the generated curve will not, in general, line up 
            with the end points of the original boundary. Therefore, we 
            construct an affine transformation matrix that translates, rotates 
            and scales the points such that the first and last points line up 
            exactly with the start and end points, respectively, of the original 
            boundary.  This transform is constructed in the following way:
            <substeps>
              <step>
                Let <inlineequation><xi:include 
                    href="resources/V_o.mml"/></inlineequation> be the vector 
                connecting the start and end points of the original boundary, 
                and <inlineequation><xi:include 
                    href="resources/V_r.mml"/></inlineequation> be similarly 
                defined for the refined boundary.
              </step>
              <step>
                The transform is the matrix
                <inlineequation>
                  <xi:include href="resources/Boundary GA - Transform Equation.mml"/>
                </inlineequation>, with:
                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                      <inlineequation>
                        <xi:include href="resources/T Matrix.mml"/>
                      </inlineequation>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                      the 2D translation along the vector from the origin to the 
                      start point of the original boundary
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                      <inlineequation>
                        <xi:include href="resources/R Matrix.mml"/>
                      </inlineequation>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                      the 2D rotation by the angle between 
                      <inlineequation><xi:include 
                      href="resources/V_o.mml"/></inlineequation> and 
                      <inlineequation><xi:include 
                      href="resources/V_r.mml"/></inlineequation>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                      <inlineequation>
                        <xi:include href="resources/S Matrix.mml"/>
                      </inlineequation>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                      the 2D scaling by the ratio <inlineequation><xi:include 
                      href="resources/Ratio V_o to V_r.mml"/></inlineequation>                  
                      </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </step>
            </substeps>
          </step>
        </procedure>
        <para>
          At this point, the original boundary has been replaced with a 
          suitable, refined version, and the operation is complete.
        </para>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="Terrain Library Analysis">
      <title>Terrain Analysis &amp; Comparison</title>
      <para>
        The second algorithmic aspect I discuss is the way in which 
        <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> analyzes and compares height 
        fields. The ability to recognize geometric and statistical similarities 
        between height fields is central to 
        <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>'s design-by-example paradigm, 
        allowing much of the labor of the terrain construction process to be 
        transferred off of the user and onto the computer.
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>Analyzing a Single Height Field</title>
        <para>
          The ultimate goal of <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> is the 
          creation of terrain models that, to a human viewer, are recognizable, 
          plausible reproductions of the kinds of terrain that the user supplied 
          as inputs. Therefore, the central question that must be asked is this: 
          what gives a "kind" of terrain its identity in the mind of the viewer?  
          A comprehensive answer to this question would involve aspects of a 
          number of disciplines, including geology, ecology, linguistics, and 
          human cognition, and is certainly outside of the scope of this 
          research. Nevertheless, for our purposes, we must arrive at a partial 
          answer to this question, one that can be quantified in terms of height 
          field geometry.
        </para>
        <para>
          Intuitively, several ways of characterizing the geometry of a height 
          field seem to be reasonable candidates for terrain type analysis.  
          First, there are the elevations and slopes in the height field (i.e., 
          the zeroth and first derivatives of the height field surface).  
          Everyday experience tells us that different kinds of terrain often 
          have very different elevation ranges and steepnesses; desert terrain, 
          for example, is generally rather flat, while mountainous terrain can 
          be extremely steep, even completely vertical in places.  Furthermore, 
          some kinds of terrain occur at characteristically different altitudes 
          (it would be unusual indeed to find a sandy beach at 10,000 feet of 
          elevation!). Empirical investigation of a number of example terrains 
          indicated that the statistical distributions of elevation and slope 
          tended to be similar between height fields of the same terrain type 
          (<xref linkend="Empirical Analysis"/>).
        </para>
        <para>
          Another way of quantitatively characterizing a height field is by the 
          presence and size of certain identifiable "features": things like 
          peaks, ridges, cliffs, rivers and gorges. Again, experience teaches us 
          to expect mountain ranges to have more pronounced peaks and ridges 
          than most other kinds of terrain, and that plains areas contain 
          primarily smooth, relatively flat ground.  Empirical investigation 
          also indicated that edge statistics tended to be similar within the 
          same terrain type.
        </para>
        <para>
          This list of height field characteristics is by no means exhaustive: a 
          number of other measures seem worthy of future investigation as 
          potential ways of terrain characterization and may ultimately turn out 
          to be more effective for comparing terrains (several possibilities are 
          discussed in <xref linkend="Enhanced Similarity Function"/>).  Even 
          so, the characteristics already mentioned are sufficient starting 
          material for a similarity function.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Comparing a Height Field to a Reference Terrain Type</title>
        <para>
          Having observed that real-world examples of the same terrain types 
          appear to exhibit similarities in their statistical behavior, we need 
          a way of quantifying this similarity. Conventional statistical 
          hypothesis tests, such as <inlineequation><xi:include 
          href="resources/chi^2.mml"/></inlineequation>, the KS test, and the t 
          test were considered, but ultimately rejected as not adaptable enough.  
          First of all, it is not enough just to test whether the means of two 
          distributions come from the same population: the mean is an ambiguous 
          indicator of terrain type (Gill remarks that the same is true when 
          distinguishing between ice and sea water in SAR imagery <biblioref 
            linkend="Ice Cover Discrimination"/>), and also tells us nothing 
          about the shape or roughness of the terrain.  Second, we need to be 
          able to accommodate <emphasis>multiple</emphasis> reference terrain 
          samples; it is not clear how to adapt a KS test, for example, to use 
          multiple reference distributions. Thus, a new kind of test is needed.
        </para>
        <para>
          Towards this end, we introduce the concept of <firstterm>Gaussian 
          curve projection</firstterm>, a technique for comparing unbounded 
          scalar values to determine the <firstterm>similarity</firstterm> of a 
          <firstterm>test value</firstterm> to one or more scalar 
          <firstterm>reference values</firstterm>.  With this as a building 
          block, we define a <firstterm>statistical distribution similarity 
          measure</firstterm> for comparing a test distribution (e.g., of 
          elevation values) to one or more reference distributions.  Finally, we 
          define an <firstterm>aggregate similarity measure</firstterm> 
          combining the distribution similarities to form an estimate of the 
          overall similarity between a height field and one or more reference 
          height fields (i.e., the height fields composing a terrain type).
        </para>

        <section id="Gaussian Curve Projection">
          <title>Gaussian Curve Projection</title>
          <para>
            Gaussian curve projection is a simple means of transforming an 
            arbitrary scalar <firstterm>test value</firstterm> into a bounded 
            <firstterm>similarity measure</firstterm>, given one or more scalar 
            <firstterm>reference values</firstterm> against which to compare the 
            test value.  The test and reference values may be either bounded or 
            unbounded, but the resulting similarity measure is guaranteed to 
            fall in the range <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/%5B0,1%5D.mml"/></inlineequation>, with values near 
            one indicating "very similar" and values near zero indicating "very 
            dissimilar".
          </para>
          <figure id="Gaussian Curve Projection Overview Diagram">
            <title>Gaussian Curve Projection</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <caption>
                Gaussian curve projection is a flexible technique for 
                transforming bounded or unbounded values into the 
                <inlineequation><xi:include 
                href="resources/%5B0,1%5D.mml"/></inlineequation> range, by 
                evaluating a Gaussian function (with a suitable mean and 
                standard deviation) at those values.
              </caption>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="Terrain Comparison - GCP Overview Diagram.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            This is accomplished by constructing a Gaussian curve based on the 
            reference values, and then finding the projection of the test value 
            onto that curve (<xref linkend="Gaussian Curve Projection Overview 
            Diagram"/>).  The curve has a height of one unit at its peak, has a 
            center value <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/mu_G.mml"/></inlineequation> equal to the mean of 
            the reference values, and has a standard deviation 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> chosen 
            "appropriately" (how <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> should be determined 
            is discussed later).  The resulting function (<xref 
            linkend="Gaussian Curve Projection Equation"/>) is capable of 
            handling any scalar value, positive or negative, yields a value of 
            one when evaluated at <inlineequation>
            <xi:include href="resources/x mu_G.mml"/></inlineequation>, and 
            yields values asymptotically approaching zero as 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/x.mml"/></inlineequation> diverges from 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/mu_G.mml"/></inlineequation>, with the rate of 
            falloff governed by the value of <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation>.
          </para>
          <equation id="Gaussian Curve Projection Equation">
            <title>Gaussian Curve Projection Equation</title>
            <xi:include href="resources/Terrain Comparison - Gaussian Curve Projection Equation.mml"/>
          </equation>
          <para>
            The only missing piece in the above formulation is the determination 
            of <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation>, which I have saved 
            for last because it deserves a slightly longer discussion.  This 
            value behaves as a sort of tolerance, controlling how wide a range 
            of values around <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/mu_G.mml"/></inlineequation> is considered  
            acceptable.  There is no "one size fits all" formula for setting 
            this parameter; instead, the parameter must be set in a manner 
            appropriate to the context in which Gaussian curve projection is 
            being used. Here are some suggestions for determining 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation>:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              If the values being compared are bounded, 
              <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> may be chosen as 
              some fraction of the total possible range of values.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              If the number of reference values is sufficiently large, then
              <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> can be chosen to 
              be the sample standard deviation of the reference values.  This 
              has the drawback that the resulting function will report some of 
              the reference values themselves as having low similarity.  This is 
              likely not what is desired, leading to the next suggestion.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              If the number of reference values is sufficiently large, then 
              <inlineequation><xi:include                   
              href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> can be chosen such 
              that all reference values evaluate to a similarity value greater 
              than or equal to some <firstterm>baseline similarity 
              value</firstterm>, <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/G_B.mml"/></inlineequation> (<xref 
              linkend="Baseline Similarity Sigma Diagram"/>).  Given a choice of 
              <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/G_B.mml"/></inlineequation>, 
              <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> may be determined  
              according to <xref linkend="Baseline Similarity Sigma Equation"/>, 
              which is obtained by rearranging <xref linkend="Gaussian Curve 
              Projection Equation"/>. This guarantees that all reference values 
              will be reported as having high similarity, and results in a 
              larger value of <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> than would be 
              produced by the previous formulation.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              If the number of reference values is too small to derive a 
              meaninful value of <inlineequation><xi:include 
                  href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation>, but there are 
              other, similar sets of reference values for which 
              <inlineequation><xi:include 
                  href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> has already 
              been determined, it may be possible to arrive at an acceptable 
              <inlineequation><xi:include 
                  href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> by deriving it 
              from the other <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation>'s (e.g., by taking 
              their mean).
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>
            These last two suggestions are what 
            <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> employs: when a suitably large 
            set of example height fields (more than one) are available for any 
            given terrain type, <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> is calculated using 
            <xref linkend="Baseline Similarity Sigma Equation"/>, with a 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/G_B.mml"/></inlineequation> of 0.9; otherwise, 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> cannot be determined 
            from the terrain type, and instead, the mean 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> of all the terrain 
            types for which <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> 
            <emphasis>could</emphasis> be determined is used as a fallback.
          </para>
          <equation id="Baseline Similarity Sigma Equation">
            <title>Baseline Similarity Equation</title>
            <xi:include href="resources/Terrain Comparison - Baseline Similarity Sigma Equation.mml"/>
          </equation>
          <figure id="Baseline Similarity Sigma Diagram">
            <title>Determining Sigma G for Multiple 
            Reference Values Using a Baseline Similarity</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <caption>
                When sufficient reference values are available, 
                <inlineequation><xi:include 
                href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> may be 
                determined by choosing a baseline similarity value, 
                <inlineequation><xi:include 
                href="resources/G_B.mml"/></inlineequation> (in this 
                example, 0.9), and selecting <inlineequation><xi:include 
                href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> such that 
                all reference values project to a similarity value greater 
                than or equal to this baseline value.
              </caption>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="Terrain Comparison - GCP Baseline Similarity Sigma Diagram.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section id="Statistical Distribution Comparison">
          <title>Comparing Statistical Distributions</title>
          <para>
            With this new tool in hand, we can now move on to comparing entire 
            statistical distributions of things (elevations, slopes, etc.). To 
            do this, we define an adaptive <firstterm>distribution similarity 
            measure</firstterm> that compares a test distribution to the 
            reference distributions on the basis of four statistical measures 
            describing the distributions:
            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
              <listitem>
                the sample mean <inlineequation><xi:include 
                    href="resources/mu.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                the sample standard deviation <inlineequation><xi:include 
                    href="resources/sigma.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                the sample skewness <inlineequation><xi:include 
                    href="resources/gamma_1.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                the sample kurtosis excess <inlineequation><xi:include 
                    href="resources/gamma_2.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            In each of these statistics, the similarity of the test distribution 
            to the reference distribution(s) is calculated using Gaussian curve 
            projection as defined above. The combined distribution similarity is 
            the weighted average of the resulting four individual similarity 
            measures (<xref linkend="Distribution Similarity Equation"/>).
          </para>
          <equation id="Distribution Similarity Equation">
            <title>Distribution Similarity Equation</title>
            <xi:include href="resources/Terrain Comparison - Distribution Similarity Equation.mml"/>
          </equation>
          <para>
            The weights assigned to the four statistics (the 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/w_i.mml"/></inlineequation>'s) must sum to 1.0, in 
            order to ensure that the combined distribution similarity measure 
            stays within the <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/%5B0,1%5D.mml"/></inlineequation> range, but they 
            are not, in general, equal. As I alluded to earlier, this 
            distribution similarity measure (<inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/S_D.mml"/></inlineequation>) is 
            <emphasis>adaptive</emphasis>, giving greater weight to individual 
            statistics (the <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/S_i.mml"/></inlineequation>'s) in which the 
            reference distributions are more unified and, similarly, giving 
            lesser weight to those in which the reference distributions diverge.  
            To understand the necessity of this adaptability, consider the case 
            where a "hills" terrain type is defined with four example height 
            fields having nearly identical distributions of elevation values, 
            except that each has a significantly different mean elevation from 
            the others (<xref linkend="The Need For Adaptability"/>).
          </para>
          <figure id="The Need For Adaptability">
            <title>The Need for Adaptability</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <caption>
                Taking as an example the case where four distributions are 
                identical, with the exception of their mean values, the need for 
                an adaptive distribution similarity measure becomes apparent.
              </caption>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="Terrain Comparison - The Need for Adaptability.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            In this case, the <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> for the standard 
            deviation, skewness, and kurtosis are all extremely small, while 
            that of the mean elevation is quite large. If, when combining the 
            individual similarity measures to form the distribution similarity 
            measure, we were to assign each measure a uniform weight of 0.25, 
            this would have the undesirable consequence of giving undue merit
            to height fields whose elevation distributions are completely unlike 
            those of the reference height fields but happen to have a mean 
            elevation within the range spanned by the examples. Because the 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> for the mean 
            elevation is large, many height fields will have a mean elevation 
            falling in the "good" zone, and would be rewarded for this with a 
            minimum similarity score of approximately 0.25. As the divergence 
            with respect to mean elevation increases, the 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> grows to embrace 
            more and more of the range of possible values, and the mean becomes 
            less and less of a differentiator (<xref linkend="A Useless 
            Statistical Measure"/>).
          </para>
          <figure id="A Useless Statistical Measure">
            <title>A Useless Statistical Measure</title>
            <caption>
              As the reference distributions diverge further and further from 
              one another, with respect to any particular statistic, that 
              statistic becomes progressively more worthless for judging the 
              similarity of a height field to that terrain type, because the 
              Gaussian function for the individual statistics's similarity grows 
              too wide to have any significant ability to differentiate.
              </caption>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="Terrain Comparison - A Useless Statistical Measure.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            Another way of stating this problem is to say that, as the 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> for a statistic 
            grows in magnitude, that statistic becomes less and less meaningful 
            for answering the question "what gives this terrain type its 
            identity?".  In the extreme case of an enormous 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation>, the statistic is 
            totally worthless (<xref linkend="A Useless Statistical Measure"/>).  
            An obvious solution is to gradually ignore individual statistics as 
            they become less useful: as the reference height fields disagree 
            more strongly on a particular statistic, the 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/sigma_G.mml"/></inlineequation> for that statistic 
            increases, and the corresponding <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/w_i.mml"/></inlineequation> for that statistic 
            should decrease (with the others increasing proportionately to keep 
            the sum of the <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/w_i.mml"/></inlineequation>'s at 1.0). Thus, for the 
            example above, the mean would be assigned a weight near 0, and the 
            other three statistics would be assigned weights near 0.33.
          </para>
          <para>
            In order to determine appropriate values for the weights, we 
            introduce another measure, the <firstterm>agreement</firstterm>.  
            The agreement describes how successfully a particular statistic 
            unites the reference distributions. We define the agreement as 1 
            minus the ratio of the curve variance to the variance of a Gaussian 
            curve that spans the entire terrain library, or zero, if the 
            variance of that statistic exceeds that of the library as a whole 
            (<xref linkend="Agreement Equation"/>).
          </para>
          <equation id="Agreement Equation">
            <title>Agreement Equation</title>
            <xi:include href="resources/Terrain Comparison - Agreement Equation.mml"/>
          </equation>
          <figure id="Agreement Diagram">
            <title>Agreement</title>
            <caption>
              The agreement of a terrain type, with respect to an individual 
              statistical measure, is a function of the ratio of that 
              statistic's similarity curve variance to that of a curve spanning 
              the whole library. Statistics that tightly cluster the example 
              height fields (<emphasis>tt1</emphasis>) are more useful and 
              exhibit a higher agreement than those in which the example height 
              fields diverge (<emphasis>tt2</emphasis>).
            </caption>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="Terrain Comparison - Agreement Diagram.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            This measure (<xref linkend="Agreement Diagram"/>) gives an idea of 
            how much confidence may be placed in the effectiveness of this 
            statistic, and also gives us a way to set the 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/w_i.mml"/></inlineequation>'s in <xref 
            linkend="Distribution Similarity Equation"/>: weights are chosen in 
            proportion to the agreement values, normalized such that they sum to 
            1 (<xref linkend="Distribution Weights Equation"/>).
          </para>
          <equation id="Distribution Weights Equation">
            <title>Distribution Weights Equation</title>
            <xi:include href="resources/Terrain Comparison - Distribution Weights Equation.mml"/>
          </equation>
          <para>
            Finally, we define the <firstterm>distribution agreement</firstterm> 
            as the mean of the four individual agreement measures (<xref 
            linkend="Distribution Agreement Equation"/>). This gives an estimate 
            of the measure of significance that the distribution similarity has: 
            if the example height fields are tightly clustered with respect to 
            each of the four individual statistics, the distribution agreement 
            will be very high.  Conversely, if all four statistics are 
            worthless, this value will be near zero.
          </para>
          <equation id="Distribution Agreement Equation">
            <title>Distribution Agreement Equation</title>
            <xi:include href="resources/Terrain Comparison - Distribution Agreement Equation.mml"/>
          </equation>
        </section>

        <section id="Terrain Similarity Evaluation">
          <title>Terrain Similarity Evaluation</title>
          <para>
            Having defined a method of comparing the statistical distribution of  
            a quantity between a single test height field and a set of reference 
            height fields, only a small step further is required to be able to 
            compare entire height fields on the basis of multiple such 
            quantities. We define the <firstterm>terrain type 
            similarity</firstterm> between a test height field and a set of 
            reference height fields to be the weighted average of the 
            distribution similarities for the following quantities (<xref 
            linkend="Terrain Type Similarity Equation"/>):
            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
              <listitem>elevation</listitem>
              <listitem>slope</listitem>
              <listitem>edge scale</listitem>
              <listitem>edge length</listitem>
              <listitem>edge strength (detector response)</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
          <equation id="Terrain Type Similarity Equation">
            <title>Terrain Type Similarity Equation</title>
            <xi:include href="resources/Terrain Comparison - Terrain Type Similarity Equation.mml"/>
          </equation>
          <para>
            As you might expect, the <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/w_i.mml"/></inlineequation>'s are defined to be 
            proportional to the respective distribution agreements, as defined 
            in <xref linkend="Distribution Agreement Equation"/>, normalized 
            such that the <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/w_i.mml"/></inlineequation>'s sum to 1 (<xref 
            linkend="Terrain Type Weights Equation"/>).
          </para>
          <equation id="Terrain Type Weights Equation">
            <title>Terrain Type Weights Equation</title>
            <xi:include href="resources/Terrain Comparison - Terrain Type Weights Equation.mml"/>
          </equation>
          <para>
            Just as the individual statistical agreements were used to attenuate 
            the effect  of a useless statistic, so also the distribution 
            agreements diminish the effect of whole distributions that do not 
            unify the reference height fields. For example, suppose that a 
            terrain type composed of 5 example height fields displays a high 
            degree of unanimity in the statistical distribution of slopes and 
            elevations, but a lesser degree of correspondence in the 
            distribution of edges.  Due to the difference in agreement measures, 
            when evaluating the similarity of a generated height field to the 
            reference terrain type, <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> will 
            demand a high degree of conformity with respect to elevation and 
            slope in order to give a high score, but will pay less attention to 
            how the height field matches with respect to the other measures. 
            Thus, characteristics in which the examples for a particular terrain 
            type are strongly united will contribute more to the overall terrain 
            similarity than will characteristics in which they diverge.
          </para>
          <para>
            One advantage to this means of comparing height fields is that it is 
            relatively immune to differences in height field size and shape: 
            because the comparison is made on the basis of statistic 
            characteristics, the height fields may be of differing sizes and 
            shapes...even non-rectangular shapes. For 
            <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle>, this is crucial, as the 
            terrain regions in the user's map are highly unlikely to be 
            rectangular. However, very small or thin regions are likely to 
            perform less well than larger regions, both because of the smaller 
            sample sizes that they represent, and because the smaller areas that 
            they cover will inhibit the formation of longer features.
          </para>
        </section>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="Height Field GA">
      <title>Height Field Construction</title>
      <para>
        The final algorithmic aspect that I discuss in depth is the height field 
        construction step. This also employs a genetic algorithm, but to solve a 
        somewhat harder problem than the boundary refinement problem (<xref 
          linkend="Boundary GA"/>).
      </para>

      <section id="Height Field GA Overview">
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>
          The height field generation algorithm is, at its heart, a multi-scale 
          image synthesis operation: the goal of this process is a height field 
          (greyscale image) of the requested size and LOD, containing plausible 
          imitations of the examples in the terrain library, arranged according 
          to the user's map. At the beginning of this step, 
          <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> has the following inputs from 
          the user (<xref linkend="Height Field GA - Inputs Diagram"/>):
        </para>
        <figure id="Height Field GA - Inputs Diagram">
          <title>Height Field GA Inputs</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Height Field GA - Inputs Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            a 2D vector map, expressing the user's desired layout for the height 
            field
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            a world-space, rectangular "active" chunk of this map, indicating 
            the particular area of the map for which a height field should be 
            generated
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            the target LOD to generate
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            a library of terrain samples, serving as examples of what the 
            terrain types referenced by the user's map should look like
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          The height field construction process proceeds in an iterative 
          fashion, starting from the coarsest possible LOD and continuing until 
          the target LOD has been reached. The coarsest LOD is constructed in a 
          nave fashion, by simply pasting together chunks of elevation data 
          from the appropriate terrain types. Each subsequent LOD is constructed 
          by the genetic algorithm, using the previous LOD as a rough "pattern" 
          to follow.
        </para>
        <para>
          The GA does not attempt to synthesize the height field from scratch; 
          instead, it takes advantage of the fact that we already 
          <emphasis>have</emphasis> realistic data for each terrain type...in 
          the terrain library. Conceptually, the genetic algorithm searches for 
          a way to blend together small chunks of terrain from the library, 
          such that the resulting terrain "makes sense":
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            each region of the height field resembles its corresponding terrain 
            type
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            the transition between regions at each boundary is smooth, without 
            unrealistic discontinuities
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            the entire height field has the same macro-scale shape as the 
            previous LOD
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          The necessity of the first two of these constraints should be 
          obvious: we want the terrain to look real. The reason for the third 
          may require some further explanation. Recall that the LOD strategy 
          used by <citetitle>Terrainosaurus</citetitle> is progressive 
          refinement (<xref linkend="Progressive Refinement Methods"/>).  
          During any run of the GA, earlier LODs have already established the 
          macro-scale features of the terrain; the job of the current run of the 
          GA is simply to add new, fine-scale detail, not to re-invent the 
          coarse-scale structure.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="Analyzing the Map">
        <title>Analyzing the Map</title>
        <para>
          The map the user created is a vector drawing. This makes a lot of 
          sense from a user-interface standpoint, since we have no way of 
          knowing <foreignphrase>a priori</foreignphrase> what LOD the user will 
          want to generate (the user himself may not know this, and even if he 
          does have a particular LOD in mind, there is no guarantee he won't 
          later decide that he needs a more detailed model). Representing the 
          map with the (virtually) infinite resolution of a vector drawing 
          allows us to defer this decision until the height field is actually 
          generated.
        </para>
        <para>
          However, since the height field we are going to generate is a raster 
          object, it will be much more convenient to have the map in a similar 
          form (i.e., a raster with the same dimensions as the height field).  
          Furthermore, once the height field generation process begins, we 
          <emphasis>do</emphasis> know the resolution of the height field we 
          are to generate, so we can safely convert the map to a raster form, 
          since the additional precision afforded by the vector representation 
          is no longer useful. At the same time, we can do some extra analysis 
          on the rasterized map that will be helpful later on. Specifically, for 
          each grid cell in the rasterized map, the quantities we calculate are:
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              the terrain type ID
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              the distance to the nearest region boundary
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              the unique ID for the enclosing terrain region
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          The first of these is simply the result of rasterizing the map. The 
          second two are derived from the first, and require segmenting the map 
          back into contiguous regions. It is worth noting that the regions 
          found at this stage may not have a 1-to-1 correspondence with those 
          in the vector-drawn map, for a variety of reasons:
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              two adjacent regions with the same terrain type are 
              indistinguishable from one another, and will be merged
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              a region that is too tiny to cover any raster cells, or which 
              falls outside of the active area of the map, will not appear in 
              the rasterized map at all, and will be eliminated
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              a concave region that only partially intersects the active area 
              of the map may have multiple, distinct fragments that fall within 
              the active area, in which case it will create multiple regions
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="Creating the Initial LOD">
        <title>Creating the Initial LOD</title>
        <para>
          Since the GA requires a "pattern" height field to follow when 
          constructing the next LOD, we cannot begin the generation process 
          without a base LOD with which to prime the GA. Obviously, this base 
          LOD cannot be constructed by the GA, so some other way of creating a 
          height field is needed.
        </para>
        <para>
          An easy way of creating this base height field is to randomly select 
          appropriately shaped chunks of elevation data from the corresponding 
          LODs of the terrain samples in the library. The discontinuities that 
          would otherwise exist at the edges between terrain types can be 
          avoided by making the selected chunks a few pixels wider around the 
          border and blending between chunks where they overlap. This can be 
          done as an image compositing operation, by constructing an 
          appropriately shaped alpha mask with an alpha value of 1 in the 
          region interior, fading to 0 just outside the region boundaries 
          (<xref linkend="Height Field GA Alpha Mask Diagram"/>). 5 pixels of 
          overlap seems to work well.
        </para>
        <figure id="Height Field GA Alpha Mask Diagram">
          <title>Alpha Mask for Constructing the Base LOD</title>
          <caption>
            The base LOD is not constructed by the GA, but is instead created 
            by combining chunks of raw data of the appropriate sizes and 
            shapes, taken from the terrain library. These chunks are blended 
            together, using an alpha mask with a linear falloff across the 
            boundaries.
          </caption>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Height Field GA - Region Alpha Mask Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Encoding &amp; Decoding a Height Field</title>
        <para>
          Once again, the problem must be expressed in a genetic encoding so 
          that the GA can work on it. In this case, the thing that needs to be 
          transformed into a set of genes is a height field.
        </para>
        <para>
          Perhaps the simplest encoding would be for every pixel in the height 
          field to be its own gene. We rejected this approach as being too 
          fine-grained: a height field of any substantial size would contain 
          thousands or millions of genes, and it is difficult to envision 
          meaningful mutation operators to work on such an encoding.
        </para>
        <para>
          In the encoding we selected, each gene represents a small, 
          <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/NxN.mml"/></inlineequation>-pixel 
          chunk of the height field, and has a terrain type and a 
          transformation associated with it.  A gene does not directly contain 
          the elevation data for its chunk of the height field; instead, it 
          holds a pointer to one of the example terrains for its terrain type, 
          and the <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/(x,y).mml"/></inlineequation> 
          coordinates within that terrain from which to copy its source data.  
          The transformation allows the source data to be rotated, translated 
          and scaled before being blended into their target location (<xref 
          linkend="Height Field GA Encoding Diagram"/>).
        </para>
        <figure id="Height Field GA Encoding Diagram">
          <title>The Encoding of a Gene in the Height Field GA</title>
          <caption>
          </caption>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Height Field GA - Encoding Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          A chromosome is a 2D grid of such genes, arranged such that each 
          gene overlaps slightly with those on each side of it (<xref 
          linkend="Height Field GA Gene Grid Diagram"/>). To prevent unseemly 
          seams from appearing between adjacent genes, we blend between adjacent 
          genes using a 2D Gaussian blending function.
        </para>
        <figure id="Height Field GA Gene Grid Diagram">
          <title>The Gene Grid</title>
          <caption>
            A chromosome in the height field GA is a 2D grid of overlapping 
            genes. Each gene has a local area of influence, within which it is 
            responsible for determining elevation values of the height field.  
            In the overlapping areas, two or more genes contribute to the height 
            field elevations, with the areas of influence smoothly blended 
            between them.
          </caption>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Height Field GA - Gene Grid Diagram.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          One benefit of this encoding is that it is relatively compact. By 
          keeping only a <emphasis>reference</emphasis> to the source height 
          field data within the gene, the chromosomes are able to be 
          substantially smaller than they would be if they carried the pixel 
          data internally (a single <inlineequation><xi:include 
          href="resources/1024x1024.mml"/></inlineequation> height field stored 
          in IEEE single-precision floating-point format is four megabytes in 
          size!). As a result, memory is not a significant factor in 
          determining the GA population size (instead, processing time is the 
          limiting factor).
        </para>
        <para>
          A second, less obvious benefit is that it is computationally 
          inexpensive. Since the gene transformation is only applied to the 
          pixel data when the chromosome is decoded, mutation operations that 
          only modify the transformation parameters can be very fast.  Also, 
          because no pixel data is stored in the gene, crossover operations are  
          faster as well.  Furthermore, many queries about the geometric 
          characteristics of a gene (mean elevation, gradient, etc.) can be 
          made quite inexpensive by precomputing these quantities for each of 
          the reference terrain samples. Then, to query these properties for a 
          gene, all that needs to be done is to look up the precomputed 
          property for the gene's source data location, accounting for any 
          transformation applied to the data.
        </para>
        <para>
          Another not-so-obvious trait of this encoding is that it is a 
          <emphasis>lossless</emphasis> encoding: it is possible to encode and 
          decode a height field using this scheme, recovering the original 
          height field exactly. It also is relatively robust against numerical 
          drift: the transformation parameters for each gene can be tweaked 
          indefinitely without corrupting the elevation data, since the 
          transformation is only applied when the chromosome is decoded back 
          into a height field, and it is always applied to the original data.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="Height Field GA Operators">
        <title>Genetic Operators</title>
        <para>
          With this encoding, a wide variety of genetic operators is possible; 
          virtually any image processing operation is a candidate, though not 
          all operations are equally reasonable. For example, a "vortex" 
          transformation on a gene is not likely to improve the terrain 
          configuration substantially, and in many cases would introduce 
          unrealistic shapes to the generated height field. On the other hand, 
          an image "rotation" transformation corresponds directly to a 
          geometric rotation of the height field surface, and could be quite 
          useful for rearranging the genes.
        </para>
        <para>
          We use a varied set of genetic operators to operate on the 
          chromosomes for the height field GA.
        </para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term> Rectangular Region Copy (crossover) </term>
            <listitem>
              This crossover operator exchanges rectangular clusters of 
              corresponding genes (i.e., genes with the same grid indices) 
              between two chromosomes.  The height and width of the copy 
              rectangle are both selected randomly from the range  
              <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/%5B1,N%5D.mml"/></inlineequation>, thus, the 
              number of copied genes falls into the range 
              <inlineequation><xi:include 
              href="resources/%5B1,N^2%5D.mml"/></inlineequation>.  The location 
              of the copy rectangle within the gene grid is randomly selected 
              such that the entire rectangle is within the grid.  This operator 
              corresponds to an image copy operation.
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term> Vertical Offset (mutation) </term>
            <listitem>
              This mutation operator modifies the vertical offset component of 
              a gene's transformation, effectively altering the mean elevation 
              of the gene. It tends to transform the gene in the direction of 
              the pattern height field's mean elevation in the vicinity of that 
              gene. This operator is similar to an image brightness adjustment 
              operation.
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term> Vertical Scale (mutation) </term>
            <listitem>
              This mutation operator modifies the vertical scale component of a 
              gene's transformation, changing the elevation range of the gene 
              without altering its mean elevation. It tends to transform the 
              gene towards having the same elevation range as the pattern 
              height field has in the vicinity of the gene. This operator 
              corresponds to linearly stretching or compressing the contrast of 
              an image.
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term> Rotation (mutation) </term>
            <listitem>
              This mutation operator modifies the rotation component of a 
              gene's transformation, effectively rotating the contents of the 
              gene about the horizontal center point of the gene. It tends to 
              transform the gene toward having the same gradient direction as 
              the pattern height field has in the vicinity of the gene. This 
              operator corresponds directly to an image rotation operation.
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term> Random Source Data Selection (mutation) </term>
            <listitem>
              This mutation operator completely replaces the source data (i.e., 
              the pointer to the source height field, and the coordinates 
              within that height field) in a gene. The new source height field 
              is randomly chosen from among the examples for the gene's terrain 
              type, and the new source coordinates are randomly chosen from 
              within that example.
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term> Horizontal Offset (mutation) </term>
            <listitem>
              This mutation operator modifies the coordinates within the source 
              terrain sample from which the gene takes its data. Like the 
              previous operator, this one has the effect of replacing the 
              gene's contents with new data, but the effect is likely to be 
              less drastic, as it keeps the same source height field and only 
              picks new source coordinates within that height field.
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>
          I said of several of the mutation operators (those that modify the 
          gene's transformation parameters) that they "tend to" adjust the 
          transformation towards conformity with the pattern height field. This 
          works by introducing a random change to the transformation parameter, 
          drawn from a Gaussian distribution centered over the value that would 
          conform the gene to the pattern (thus, this value has the highest 
          probability of being chosen, but a nearby value may be chosen 
          instead).
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="Height Field GA Fitness Evaluation">
        <title>Fitness Evaluation</title>
        <para>
          Finally, we come to the crux of the matter: how does the GA discern 
          between good height fields and bad ones? The fitness evaluation is 
          separated into two aspects, and we calculate the overall fitness as a 
          weighted combination of the two (<xref linkend="Height Field Fitness 
            Equation"/>).
        </para>
        <equation id="Height Field Fitness Equation">
          <title>Height Field Fitness Equation</title>
          <xi:include href="resources/Height Field GA - Fitness Equation.mml"/>
        </equation>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/C_g.mml"/></inlineequation>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              geometric compatibility
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/S_r.mml"/></inlineequation>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              regional terrain type similarity
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/Alpha.mml"/></inlineequation>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              a weighting coefficient, controlling how strongly each component 
              affects the overall fitness; 0.5 was found experimentally to be a 
              reasonable value
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <section>
          <title>Geometric Compatibility</title>
          <para>
            <firstterm>Geometric compatibility</firstterm> describes how well 
            the height field encoded in the chromosome matches the "pattern" 
            provided by the previous LOD. This is important for ensuring that 
            the generated LOD is conforming to the macro-scale features 
            constructed by the previous LODs. The compatibility of a chromosome 
            can be estimated directly from the genetic representation, by 
            comparing the mean elevation and the mean gradient over each gene's 
            area of influence with those values for the corresponding areas of 
            the pattern height field.
          </para>
          <para>
            In comparing these geometric properties, we encounter the same 
            difficulty that we did earlier, in our discussion of comparing 
            statistical distributions: we are trying to compare two unbounded 
            quantities, to get a compatibility measure in the bounded range 
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/%5B0,1%5D.mml"/></inlineequation>.  We employ the 
            same solution to this problem here as we did to the other instance: 
            a Gaussian curve projection.  In this case, the  curve mean is the 
            value of the pattern height field that we're trying to match, and 
            the curve standard deviation is chosen to be one fourth the range 
            for the gene's terrain type (e.g., for a "mountain" gene, the curve 
            standard deviation would be one fourth of the elevation range for 
            the "mountain" terrain type).  Again, the choice of standard 
            deviation is somewhat arbitrary, but this value seems to work well, 
            allowing a moderate amount of disagreement between a gene and the 
            pattern before the gene starts to be heavily penalized. The total 
            compatibility of a gene is then calculated from <xref linkend="Gene 
            Compatibility Equation"/>.
          </para>
          <equation id="Gene Compatibility Equation">
            <title>Gene Compatibility Equation</title>
            <xi:include href="resources/Height Field GA - Gene Compatibility Equation.mml"/>
          </equation>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
                <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/C_g,i.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                overall compatibility for gene <inlineequation><xi:include 
                href="resources/i.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
                <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/E_i.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                mean elevation over gene <inlineequation><xi:include 
                href="resources/i.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
                <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/M_i.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                mean gradient magnitude (slope) over gene 
                <inlineequation><xi:include 
                href="resources/i.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
                <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/A_i.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                mean gradient angle over gene <inlineequation><xi:include 
                href="resources/i.mml"/></inlineequation>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          <para>
            The aggregate compatibility of the entire chromosome 
            (<inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/C_g.mml"/></inlineequation>) is 
            then simply the mean of all of the <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/C_g,i.mml"/></inlineequation>'s.
          </para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Regional Terrain Type Similarity</title>
          <para>
            The second aspect of height field fitness is the regional terrain 
            type similarity: how similar each region is to the examples that 
            make up its corresponding terrain type, in terms of measurable 
            characteristics.
          </para>
          <para>
            The similarity of each individual region is calculated just as 
            described in <xref linkend="Terrain Library Analysis"/>. For the 
            aggregate similarity of the whole height field, however, rather than 
            simply using the arithmetic mean of the individual regional 
            similarities, we instead calculate the area-weighted mean, using the 
            proportion of pixels within each region as the weight for that 
            region's similarity. This reduces the impact that small regions have 
            on the overall fitness of the terrain.
          </para>
        </section>

        <section id="Localized Guidance">
          <title>Localized Guidance of the Genetic Algorithm</title>
          <para>
            As is the case for many things, the GA's great strength can also be 
            a weakness. GAs can solve optimization problems in which the 
            effects of changes are not well understood, precisely because the 
            GA is agnostic about the internal interactions, only evaluating the 
            outcomes. Unfortunately, this also means that a standard GA is 
            rather "dumb": it does not take advantage of domain-specific 
            knowledge that might help guide the GA more quickly in the direction 
            of an optimal solution (or, at least, <emphasis>away</emphasis> from 
            truly horrible solutions).  When the chromosome size is large, the 
            contribution of any individual gene to the overall fitness is highly 
            diluted, thus an "error" in a gene may take a long time to be fixed, 
            and convergence will be slow.
          </para>
          <para>
            To address this, we modify the GA to retain additional information 
            from the fitness evaluation, and we use this information to adjust 
            the probability of a mutation occurring in a gene and also to 
            influence the probability distribution function for choosing which 
            mutation operator is invoked.
          </para>
          <para>
            We do this in several places in the GA. At the region level, we 
            retain the region similarity measure, using it to increase or 
            decrease the mutation probabilities of the genes within that region.  
            Similarly, at the gene level, we retain the individual compatibility 
            components, as well as the overall compatibility measure. The 
            probability of a gene being mutated is calculated using <xref 
              linkend="Height Field GA Mutation Probability Equation"/>:
          </para>
          <equation id="Height Field GA Mutation Probability Equation">
            <title>Gene Mutation Probability</title>
            <xi:include href="resources/Height Field GA - Mutation Probability Equation.mml"/>
          </equation>
          <para>
            where <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/P_m.mml"/></inlineequation> 
            is the baseline probability of mutation.  With this formulation, 
            the baseline mutation probability still has a strong effect, but 
            genes in highly dissimilar regions and genes that are highly 
            incompatible with the underlying pattern are substantially more 
            likely to be mutated.
          </para>
          <para>
            Once the GA decides to mutate a particular gene, it still has to 
            choose which mutation operator it will apply. An attractive feature 
            of this enhancement to the GA is that smart and dumb mutation 
            operators may be freely intermixed. A <firstterm>smart</firstterm> 
            mutation operator is one that has a predictable relationship to 
            some component of the fitness evaluation (e.g., 
            <inlineequation><xi:include href="resources/E_i.mml"/></inlineequation>, the 
            mean elevation of a gene, is directly affected by the "vertical 
            offset" operator).  In contrast, a <firstterm>dumb</firstterm> 
            genetic operator produces unpredictable effects, or else cannot 
            easily be related to any part of the fitness evaluation (e.g., the 
            "pick new source location" operator). When deciding which operator 
            to use, the GA modifies the mutation operator probability 
            distribution function (PDF), giving higher probabilities to smart 
            operators that are needed by the current gene and lower 
            probabilities to smart operators that are not.  Probabilities for 
            dumb operators remain fixed.
          </para>
          <para>
            One way to understand these changes to the GA is as additional, 
            tighter feedback loops within the GA, essentially creating several 
            child GAs within the height field generation GA, who are better 
            equipped to handle particular aspects of the problem. One point 
            that deserves to be mentioned is that, despite incorporating this 
            additional guidance, the algorithm is still a 
            <emphasis>probabilistic</emphasis> algorithm, not a deterministic 
            one. While a speedier convergence rate is generally a good thing, we 
            want to retain the randomness and diversity of the GA, so as not to 
            lose the ability to escape local maxima in the solution space (i.e., 
            terrains that are "OK" but not "great").
          </para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Cleaning Up the Final Result</title>
          <para>
            A final improvement we can make concerns those few genes that are 
            out-of-place at the end of the GA. Given enough evolution cycles, 
            the GA is generally successful at bringing 
            <emphasis>most</emphasis> of the genes into alignment, however, 
            since it is a probabilistic algorithm, it is not unlikely that a 
            handful of genes out of the dozens (or hundreds) in the chromosome 
            might escape being brought into conformity with the rest. Such 
            genes are especially noticeable if they have a substantially 
            different elevation from the surrounding terrain; they look sort of  
            like squarish "fingers" poking up from the ground (<xref 
              linkend="Terrain Fingers"/>).
          </para>
          <figure id="Terrain Fingers">
            <title>Unaligned Genes Look Like "Fingers"</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata scalefit="1" width="4in"
                           fileref="Terrain Fingers.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            These remaining artifacts can be removed by applying a 
            <firstterm>conform</firstterm> operator to these aberrant genes.  
            The conform operator simply sets the gene's transformation 
            parameters so as to give the gene a compatibility value
            <inlineequation><xi:include 
            href="resources/C_g,i.mml"/></inlineequation> of 1; in effect, it 
            forces the gene to fit the pattern height field as closely as 
            possible.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

  </section>
</chapter>
